[
    {
        "id": 1,
        "Question": "The ______ format is usually used to store data.",
        "Options": [
            "a) BCD",
            "b) Decimal",
            "c) Hexadecimal",
            "d) Octal"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The data usually used by computers have to be stored and represented in a particular format for ease of use. "
    },
    {
        "id": 2,
        "Question": "The 8-bit encoding format used to store data in a computer is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ASCII",
            "b) EBCDIC",
            "c) ANCI",
            "d) USCII"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The data to be stored in the computers have to be encoded in a particular way so as to provide secure processing of the data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 3,
        "Question": "A source program is usually in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Assembly language",
            "b) Machine level language",
            "c) High-level language",
            "d) Natural language"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The program written and before being compiled or assembled is called as a source program."
    },
    {
        "id": 4,
        "Question": "Which memory device is generally made of semiconductors?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAM",
            "b) Hard-disk",
            "c) Floppy disk",
            "d) Cd disk"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: Memory devices are usually made of semiconductors for faster manipulation of the contents."
    },
    {
        "id": 5,
        "Question": "The small extremely fast, RAM’s are called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cache",
            "b) Heaps",
            "c) Accumulators",
            "d) Stacks"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: These small and fast memory devices are compared to RAM because they optimize the performance of the system and they only keep files which are required by the current process in them "
    },
    {
        "id": 6,
        "Question": "The ALU makes use of _______ to store the intermediate results.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Accumulators",
            "b) Registers",
            "c) Heap",
            "d) Stack"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The ALU is the computational center of the CPU. It performs all mathematical and logical operations. In order to perform better, it uses some internal memory spaces to store immediate results."
    },
    {
        "id": 7,
        "Question": "The control unit controls other units by generating ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control signals",
            "b) Timing signals",
            "c) Transfer signals",
            "d) Command Signals"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This unit is used to control and coordinate between the various parts and components of the CPU.\n"
    },
    {
        "id": 8,
        "Question": "______ are numbers and encoded characters, generally used as operands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Input",
            "b) Data",
            "c) Information",
            "d) Stored Values"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 9,
        "Question": "The Input devices can send information to the processor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) When the SIN status flag is set",
            "b) When the data arrives regardless of the SIN flag",
            "c) Neither of the cases",
            "d) Either of the cases"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The input devices use buffers to store the data received and when the buffer has some data it sends it to the processor. "
    },
    {
        "id": 10,
        "Question": "______ bus structure is usually used to connect I/O devices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single bus",
            "b) Multiple bus",
            "c) Star bus",
            "d) Rambus"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: BUS is a bunch of wires which carry address, control signals and data. It is used to connect various components of the computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 11,
        "Question": "The I/O interface required to connect the I/O device to the bus consists of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Address decoder and registers",
            "b) Control circuits",
            "c) Address decoder, registers and Control circuits",
            "d) Only Control circuits"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The I/O devices are connected to the CPU via BUS and to interact with the BUS they have an interface."
    },
    {
        "id": 12,
        "Question": "To reduce the memory access time we generally make use of  ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heaps",
            "b) Higher capacity RAM’s",
            "c) SDRAM’s",
            "d) Cache’s"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The time required to access a part of the memory for data retrieval. "
    },
    {
        "id": 13,
        "Question": "______ is generally used to increase the apparent size of physical memory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary memory",
            "b) Virtual memory",
            "c) Hard-disk",
            "d) Disks"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Virtual memory is like an extension to the existing memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 14,
        "Question": "MFC stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory Format Caches",
            "b) Memory Function Complete",
            "c) Memory Find Command",
            "d) Mass Format Command"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This is a system command enabled when a memory function is completed by a process."
    },
    {
        "id": 15,
        "Question": "The time delay between two successive initiations of memory operation _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory access time",
            "b) Memory search time",
            "c) Memory cycle time",
            "d) Instruction delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The time is taken to finish one task and to start another."
    },
    {
        "id": 16,
        "Question": "The decoded instruction is stored in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) IR",
            "b) PC",
            "c) Registers",
            "d) MDR"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The instruction after obtained from the PC, is decoded and operands are fetched and stored in the IR. "
    },
    {
        "id": 17,
        "Question": "The instruction -> Add LOCA, R0 does _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adds the value of LOCA to R0 and stores in the temp register",
            "b) Adds the value of R0 to the address of LOCA",
            "c) Adds the values of both LOCA and R0 and stores it in R0",
            "d) Adds the value of LOCA with a value in accumulator and stores it in R0"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 18,
        "Question": "Which registers can interact with the secondary storage?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAR",
            "b) PC",
            "c) IR",
            "d) R0"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: MAR can interact with secondary storage in order to fetch data from it."
    },
    {
        "id": 19,
        "Question": "During the execution of a program which gets initialized first?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MDR",
            "b) IR",
            "c) PC",
            "d) MAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: For the execution of a process first the instruction is placed in the PC. "
    },
    {
        "id": 20,
        "Question": "Which of the register/s of the processor is/are connected to Memory Bus?",
        "Options": [
            "a) PC",
            "b) MAR",
            "c) IR",
            "d) Both PC and MAR"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: MAR is connected to the memory BUS in order to access the memory. "
    },
    {
        "id": 21,
        "Question": "ISP stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Instruction Set Processor",
            "b) Information Standard Processing",
            "c) Interchange Standard Protocol",
            "d) Interrupt Service Procedure"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 22,
        "Question": "The internal components of the processor are connected by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor intra-connectivity circuitry",
            "b) Processor bus",
            "c) Memory bus",
            "d) Rambus"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The processor BUS is used to connect the various parts in order to provide a direct connection to the CPU.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 23,
        "Question": "______ is used to choose between incrementing the PC or performing ALU operations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conditional codes",
            "b) Multiplexer",
            "c) Control unit",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The multiplexer circuit is used to choose between the two as it can give different results based on the input. "
    },
    {
        "id": 24,
        "Question": "The registers, ALU and the interconnection between them are collectively called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) process route",
            "b) information trail",
            "c) information path",
            "d) data path"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The Operational and processing part of the CPU are collectively called as a data path. "
    },
    {
        "id": 25,
        "Question": "_______ is used to store data in registers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) D flip flop",
            "b) JK flip flop",
            "c) RS flip flop",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 26,
        "Question": "The main virtue for using single Bus structure is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast data transfers",
            "b) Cost effective connectivity and speed",
            "c) Cost effective connectivity and ease of attaching peripheral devices",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: By using a single BUS structure we can minimize the amount of hardware (wire) required and thereby reducing the cost."
    },
    {
        "id": 27,
        "Question": "______ are used to overcome the difference in data transfer speeds of various devices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Speed enhancing circuitory",
            "b) Bridge circuits",
            "c) Multiple Buses",
            "d) Buffer registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: By using Buffer registers, the processor sends the data to the I/O device at the processor speed and the data gets stored in the buffer. After that the data gets sent to or from the buffer to the devices at the device speed."
    },
    {
        "id": 28,
        "Question": "To extend the connectivity of the processor bus we use ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI bus",
            "b) SCSI bus",
            "c) Controllers",
            "d) Multiple bus"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: PCI BUS is used to connect other peripheral devices that require a direct connection with the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 29,
        "Question": "IBM developed a bus standard for their line of computers ‘PC AT’ called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) IB bus",
            "b) M-bus",
            "c) ISA",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 30,
        "Question": "The bus used to connect the monitor to the CPU is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI bus",
            "b) SCSI bus",
            "c) Memory bus",
            "d) Rambus"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: SCSI BUS is usually used to connect video devices to the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 31,
        "Question": "ANSI stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) American National Standards Institute",
            "b) American National Standard Interface",
            "c) American Network Standard Interfacing",
            "d) American Network Security Interrupt"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 32,
        "Question": "_____ register Connected to the Processor bus is a single-way transfer capable.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PC",
            "b) IR",
            "c) Temp",
            "d) Z"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The Z register is a special register which can interact with the processor BUS only."
    },
    {
        "id": 33,
        "Question": "In multiple Bus organisation, the registers are collectively placed and referred as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set registers",
            "b) Register file",
            "c) Register Block",
            "d) Map registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 34,
        "Question": "The main advantage of multiple bus organisation over a single bus is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in the number of cycles for execution",
            "b) Increase in size of the registers",
            "c) Better Connectivity",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 35,
        "Question": "The ISA standard Buses are used to connect ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAM and processor",
            "b) GPU and processor",
            "c) Harddisk and Processor",
            "d) CD/DVD drives and Processor"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 36,
        "Question": "During the execution of the instructions, a copy of the instructions is placed in the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Register",
            "b) RAM",
            "c) System heap",
            "d) Cache"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 37,
        "Question": "Two processors A and B have clock frequencies of 700 Mhz and 900 Mhz respectively. Suppose A can execute an instruction with an average of 3 steps and B can execute with an average of 5 steps. For the execution of the same instruction which processor is faster?",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) Both take the same time",
            "d) Insufficient information"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The performance of a system can be found out using the Basic performance formula."
    },
    {
        "id": 38,
        "Question": "A processor performing fetch or decoding of different instruction during the execution of another instruction is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Super-scaling",
            "b) Pipe-lining",
            "c) Parallel Computation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Pipe-lining is the process of improving the performance of the system by processing different instructions at the same time, with only one instruction performing one specific operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 39,
        "Question": "For a given FINITE number of instructions to be executed, which architecture of the processor provides for a faster execution?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ISA",
            "b) ANSA",
            "c) Super-scalar",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: In super-scalar architecture, the instructions are set in groups and they’re decoded and executed together reducing the amount of time required to process them."
    },
    {
        "id": 40,
        "Question": "The clock rate of the processor can be improved by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Improving the IC technology of the logic circuits",
            "b) Reducing the amount of processing done in one step",
            "c) By using the overclocking method",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The clock rate(frequency of the processor) is the hardware dependent quantity it is fixed for a given processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 41,
        "Question": "An optimizing Compiler does _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Better compilation of the given piece of code",
            "b) Takes advantage of the type of processor and reduces its process time",
            "c) Does better memory management",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: An optimizing compiler is a compiler designed for the specific purpose of increasing the operation speed of the processor by reducing the time taken to compile the program instructions."
    },
    {
        "id": 42,
        "Question": "The ultimate goal of a compiler is to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduce the clock cycles for a programming task",
            "b) Reduce the size of the object code",
            "c) Be versatile",
            "d) Be able to detect even the smallest of errors"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 43,
        "Question": "SPEC stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Standard Performance Evaluation Code",
            "b) System Processing Enhancing Code",
            "c) System Performance Evaluation Corporation",
            "d) Standard Processing Enhancement Corporation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: SPEC is a corporation that started to standardize the evaluation method of a system’s performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 44,
        "Question": "As of 2000, the reference system to find the performance of a system is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ultra SPARC 10",
            "b) SUN SPARC",
            "c) SUN II",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In SPEC system of measuring a system’s performance, a system is used as a reference against which other systems are compared and performance is determined."
    },
    {
        "id": 45,
        "Question": "When Performing a looping operation, the instruction gets stored in the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Registers",
            "b) Cache",
            "c) System Heap",
            "d) System stack"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: When a looping or branching operation is carried out the offset value is stored in the cache along with the data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 46,
        "Question": "The average number of steps taken to execute the set of instructions can be made to be less than one by following _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ISA",
            "b) Pipe-lining",
            "c) Super-scaling",
            "d) Sequential"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The number of steps required to execute a given set of instructions is sufficiently reduced by using super-scaling. In this method, a set of instructions are grouped together and are processed."
    },
    {
        "id": 47,
        "Question": "If a processor clock is rated as 1250 million cycles per second, then its clock period is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1.9 * 10-10 sec",
            "b) 1.6 * 10-9 sec",
            "c) 1.25 * 10-10 sec",
            "d) 8 * 10-10 sec"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 48,
        "Question": "If the instruction, Add R1, R2, R3 is executed in a system that is pipe-lined, then the value of S is (Where S is a term of the Basic performance equation)?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) ~2",
            "c) ~1",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: S is the number of steps required to execute the instructions."
    },
    {
        "id": 49,
        "Question": "CISC stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete Instruction Sequential Compilation",
            "b) Computer Integrated Sequential Compiler",
            "c) Complex Instruction Set Computer",
            "d) Complex Instruction Sequential Compilation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: CISC is a type of system architecture where complex instructions are grouped together and executed to improve system performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 50,
        "Question": "As of 2000, the reference system to find the SPEC rating are built with _____ Processor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intel Atom SParc 300Mhz",
            "b) Ultra SPARC -IIi 300MHZ",
            "c) Amd Neutrino series",
            "d) ASUS A series 450 Mhz"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 51,
        "Question": "The instruction, Add #45,R1 does _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Adds the value of 45 to the address of R1 and stores 45 in that address",
            "b) Adds 45 to the value of R1 and stores it in R1",
            "c) Finds the memory location 45 and adds that content to that of R1",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The instruction is using immediate addressing mode hence the value is stored in the location 45 is added. "
    },
    {
        "id": 52,
        "Question": "In the case of, Zero-address instruction method the operands are stored in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Registers",
            "b) Accumulators",
            "c) Push down stack",
            "d) Cache"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case, the operands are implicitly loaded onto the ALU. "
    },
    {
        "id": 53,
        "Question": "Add #45, when this instruction is executed the following happen/s _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The processor raises an error and requests for one more operand",
            "b) The value stored in memory location 45 is retrieved and one more operand is requested",
            "c) The value 45 gets added to the value on the stack and is pushed onto the stack",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 54,
        "Question": "The addressing mode which makes use of in-direction pointers is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirect addressing mode",
            "b) Index addressing mode",
            "c) Relative addressing mode",
            "d) Offset addressing mode"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In this addressing mode, the value of the register serves as another memory location and hence we use pointers to get the data.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 55,
        "Question": "In the following indexed addressing mode instruction, MOV 5(R1), LOC the effective address is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) EA = 5+R1",
            "b) EA = R1",
            "c) EA = [R1] ",
            "d) EA = 5+[R1]"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: This instruction is in Base with offset addressing mode.    "
    },
    {
        "id": 56,
        "Question": "The addressing mode/s, which uses the PC instead of a general purpose register is  ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indexed with offset",
            "b) Relative",
            "c) Direct",
            "d) Both Indexed with offset and direct"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In this, the contents of the PC are directly incremented. "
    },
    {
        "id": 57,
        "Question": "The addressing mode, where you directly specify the operand value is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Immediate",
            "b) Direct",
            "c) Definite",
            "d) Relative"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: In the case of, auto increment the increment is done afterward and in auto decrement the decrement is done first.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 58,
        "Question": "The effective address of the following instruction is MUL 5(R1,R2).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5+R1+R2",
            "b) 5+(R1*R2)",
            "c) 5+[R1]+[R2] ",
            "d) 5*([R1]+[R2])"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 59,
        "Question": "_____ addressing mode is most suitable to change the normal sequence of execution of instructions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relative",
            "b) Indirect",
            "c) Index with Offset",
            "d) Immediate"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The addressing mode used is base with offset and index. "
    },
    {
        "id": 60,
        "Question": "Which method/s of representation of numbers occupies a large amount of memory than others?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sign-magnitude",
            "b) 1’s complement",
            "c) 2’s complement",
            "d) 1’s & 2’s compliment"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: It takes more memory as one bit used up to store the sign. "
    },
    {
        "id": 61,
        "Question": "Which representation is most efficient to perform arithmetic operations on the numbers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sign-magnitude",
            "b) 1’s complement",
            "c) 2’S complement",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The two’s complement form is more suitable to perform arithmetic operations as there is no need to involve the sign of the number into consideration.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 62,
        "Question": "Which method of representation has two representations for ‘0’?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sign-magnitude",
            "b) 1’s complement",
            "c) 2’s complement",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: One is positive and one for negative. "
    },
    {
        "id": 63,
        "Question": "When we perform subtraction on -7 and 1 the answer in 2’s complement form is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1010",
            "b) 1110",
            "c) 0110",
            "d) 1000"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: First the 2’s complement is found and that is added to the number and the overflow is ignored. "
    },
    {
        "id": 64,
        "Question": "When we perform subtraction on -7 and -5 the answer in 2’s complement form is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 11110",
            "b) 1110",
            "c) 1010",
            "d) 0010"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: First the 2’s complement is found and that is added to the number and the overflow is ignored.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 65,
        "Question": "When we subtract -3 from 2 , the answer in 2’s complement form is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0001",
            "b) 1101",
            "c) 0101",
            "d) 1001"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: First the 2’s complement is found and that is added to the number and the overflow is ignored.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 66,
        "Question": "The processor keeps track of the results of its operations using flags called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Conditional code flags",
            "b) Test output flags",
            "c) Type flags",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: These flags are used to indicate if there is an overflow or carry or zero result occurrence."
    },
    {
        "id": 67,
        "Question": "The register used to store the flags is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flag register",
            "b) Status register",
            "c) Test register",
            "d) Log register"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The status register stores the condition codes of the system.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 68,
        "Question": "The Flag ‘V’ is set to 1 indicates that _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The operation is valid",
            "b) The operation is validated",
            "c) The operation has resulted in an overflow",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This is used to check the overflow occurs in the operation. "
    },
    {
        "id": 69,
        "Question": "In some pipelined systems, a different instruction is used to add to numbers which can affect the flags upon execution. That instruction is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) AddSetCC",
            "b) AddCC",
            "c) Add++",
            "d) SumSetCC"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: By using this instruction the condition flags won’t be affected at all. "
    },
    {
        "id": 70,
        "Question": "The most efficient method followed by computers to multiply two unsigned numbers is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Booth algorithm",
            "b) Bit pair recording of multipliers",
            "c) Restoring algorithm",
            "d) Non restoring algorithm"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 71,
        "Question": "For the addition of large integers, most of the systems make use of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast adders",
            "b) Full adders",
            "c) Carry look-ahead adders",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: In this method, the carries for each step are generated first. "
    },
    {
        "id": 72,
        "Question": "In a normal n-bit adder, to find out if an overflow as occurred we make use of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) And gate",
            "b) Nand gate",
            "c) Nor gate",
            "d) Xor gate"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 73,
        "Question": "In the implementation of a Multiplier circuit in the system we make use of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Counter",
            "b) Flip flop",
            "c) Shift register",
            "d) Push down stack"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The shift registers are used to store the multiplied answer.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 74,
        "Question": "When 1101 is used to divide 100010010 the remainder is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 101",
            "b) 11",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 75,
        "Question": "The smallest entity of memory is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cell",
            "b) Block",
            "c) Instance",
            "d) Unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: Each data is made up of a number of units. "
    },
    {
        "id": 76,
        "Question": "The collection of the above mentioned entities where data is stored is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Block",
            "b) Set",
            "c) Word",
            "d) Byte"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: Each readable part of the data is called blocks. "
    },
    {
        "id": 77,
        "Question": "An 24 bit address generates an address space of ______ locations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1024",
            "b) 4096",
            "c) 248",
            "d) 16,777,216"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The number of addressable locations in the system is called as address space.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 78,
        "Question": "If a system is 64 bit machine, then the length of each word will be _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 bytes",
            "b) 8 bytes",
            "c) 16 bytes",
            "d) 12 bytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: A 64 bit system means, that at a time 64 bit instruction can be executed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 79,
        "Question": "The type of memory assignment used in Intel processors is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Little Endian",
            "b) Big Endian",
            "c) Medium Endian",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The method of address allocation to data to be stored is called as memory assignment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 80,
        "Question": "When using the Big Endian assignment to store a number, the sign bit of the number is stored in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) The higher order byte of the word",
            "b) The lower order byte of the word",
            "c) Can’t say",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 81,
        "Question": "To get the physical address from the logical address generated by CPU we use ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAR",
            "b) MMU",
            "c) Overlays",
            "d) TLB"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Memory Management Unit, is used to add the offset to the logical address generated by the CPU to get the physical address.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 82,
        "Question": "_____ method is used to map logical addresses of variable length onto physical memory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paging",
            "b) Overlays",
            "c) Segmentation",
            "d) Paging with segmentation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: Segmentation is a process in which memory is divided into groups of variable length called segments.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 83,
        "Question": "During the transfer of data between the processor and memory we use  ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cache",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) Buffers",
            "d) Registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 84,
        "Question": "Physical memory is divided into sets of finite size called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frames",
            "b) Pages",
            "c) Blocks",
            "d) Vectors"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 85,
        "Question": "Add #%01011101,R1 , when this instruction is executed then _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The binary addition between the operands takes place",
            "b) The Numerical value represented by the binary value is added to the value of R1",
            "c) The addition doesn’t take place, whereas this is similar to a MOV instruction",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This performs operations in binary mode directly. "
    },
    {
        "id": 86,
        "Question": "If we want to perform memory or arithmetic operations on data in Hexa-decimal mode then we use _________ symbol before the operand.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ~",
            "b) !",
            "c) $",
            "d) *"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 87,
        "Question": "When generating physical addresses from a logical address the offset is stored in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Translation look-aside buffer",
            "b) Relocation register",
            "c) Page table",
            "d) Shift register"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In the MMU the relocation register stores the offset address. "
    },
    {
        "id": 88,
        "Question": "The technique used to store programs larger than the memory is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overlays",
            "b) Extension registers",
            "c) Buffers",
            "d) Both Extension registers and Buffers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In this, only a part of the program getting executed is stored on the memory and later swapped in for the other part. "
    },
    {
        "id": 89,
        "Question": "The unit which acts as an intermediate agent between memory and backing store to reduce process time is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) TLB’s",
            "b) Registers",
            "c) Page tables",
            "d) Cache"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The cache’s help in data transfers by storing most recently used memory pages."
    },
    {
        "id": 90,
        "Question": "Does the Load instruction do the following operation/s?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loads the contents of a disc onto a memory location",
            "b) Loads the contents of a location onto the accumulators",
            "c) Load the contents of the PCB onto the register",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The load instruction is basically used to load the contents of a memory location onto a register.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 91,
        "Question": "Complete the following analogy:- Registers are to RAM’s as Cache’s are to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) System stacks",
            "b) Overlays",
            "c) Page Table",
            "d) TLB"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 92,
        "Question": "The BOOT sector files of the system are stored in ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Harddisk",
            "b) ROM",
            "c) RAM",
            "d) Fast solid state chips in the motherboard"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The files which are required for the starting up of a system are stored on the ROM. "
    },
    {
        "id": 93,
        "Question": "The transfer of large chunks of data with the involvement of the processor is done by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) DMA controller",
            "b) Arbitrator",
            "c) User system programs",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This mode of transfer involves the transfer of a large block of data from the memory.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 94,
        "Question": "Which of the following techniques used to effectively utilize main memory?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Address binding",
            "b) Dynamic linking",
            "c) Dynamic loading",
            "d) Both  Dynamic linking and loading"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: In this method only when the routine is required is loaded and hence saves memory.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 95,
        "Question": "RTN stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Register Transfer Notation",
            "b) Register Transmission Notation",
            "c) Regular Transmission Notation",
            "d) Regular Transfer Notation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the way of writing the assembly language code with the help of register notations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 96,
        "Question": "The instruction, Add Loc,R1 in RTN is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) AddSetCC Loc+R1",
            "b) R1=Loc+R1",
            "c) Not possible to write in RTN",
            "d) R1<-[Loc]+[R1]"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 97,
        "Question": "Can you perform an addition on three operands simultaneously in ALN using Add instruction?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Yes",
            "b) Not possible using Add, we’ve to use AddSetCC",
            "c) Not permitted",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: You cannot perform an addition on three operands simultaneously because the third operand is where the result is stored.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 98,
        "Question": "The instruction, Add R1,R2,R3 in RTN is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) R3=R1+R2+R3",
            "b) R3<-[R1]+[R2]+[R3] ",
            "c) R3=[R1]+[R2] ",
            "d) R3<-[R1]+[R2]"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: In RTN the first operand is the destination and the second operand is the source. "
    },
    {
        "id": 99,
        "Question": "In a system, which has 32 registers the register id is __________ long.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16 bit",
            "b) 8 bits",
            "c) 5 bits",
            "d) 6 bits"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The ID is the name tag given to each of the registers and used to identify them. "
    },
    {
        "id": 100,
        "Question": "The two phases of executing an instruction are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Instruction decoding and storage",
            "b) Instruction fetch and instruction execution",
            "c) Instruction execution and storage",
            "d) Instruction fetch and Instruction processing"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: First, the instructions are fetched and decoded and then they’re executed and stored. "
    },
    {
        "id": 101,
        "Question": "The Instruction fetch phase ends with _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Placing the data from the address in MAR into MDR",
            "b) Placing the address of the data into MAR",
            "c) Completing the execution of the data and placing its storage address into MAR",
            "d) Decoding the data in MDR and placing it in IR"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The fetch ends with the instruction getting decoded and being placed in the IR and the PC getting incremented. "
    },
    {
        "id": 102,
        "Question": "While using the iterative construct (Branching) in execution _____________ instruction is used to check the condition.",
        "Options": [
            "a) TestAndSet",
            "b) Branch",
            "c) TestCondn",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Branch instruction is used to check the test condition and to perform the memory jump with the help of offset. "
    },
    {
        "id": 103,
        "Question": "When using Branching, the usual sequencing of the PC is altered. A new instruction is loaded which is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Branch target",
            "b) Loop target",
            "c) Forward target",
            "d) Jump instruction"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 104,
        "Question": "The condition flag Z is set to 1 to indicate _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The operation has resulted in an error",
            "b) The operation requires an interrupt call",
            "c) The result is zero",
            "d) There is no empty register available"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This condition flag is used to check if the arithmetic operation yields a zero output. "
    },
    {
        "id": 105,
        "Question": "__________ converts the programs written in assembly language into machine instructions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Machine compiler",
            "b) Interpreter",
            "c) Assembler",
            "d) Converter"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: An assembler is a software used to convert the programs into machine instructions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 106,
        "Question": "The instructions like MOV or ADD are called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) OP-Code",
            "b) Operators",
            "c) Commands",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This OP – codes tell the system what operation to perform on the operands. "
    },
    {
        "id": 107,
        "Question": "The alternate way of writing the instruction, ADD #5,R1 is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ADD [5],[R1];",
            "b) ADDI 5,R1;",
            "c) ADDIME 5,[R1];",
            "d) There is no other way"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The ADDI instruction, means the addition is in immediate addressing mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 108,
        "Question": "Instructions which won’t appear in the object program are called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Redundant instructions",
            "b) Exceptions",
            "c) Comments",
            "d) Assembler Directives"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The directives help the program in getting compiled and hence won’t be there in the object code.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 109,
        "Question": "The assembler directive EQU, when used in the instruction: Sum EQU 200 does ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Finds the first occurrence of Sum and assigns value 200 to it",
            "b) Replaces every occurrence of Sum with 200",
            "c) Re-assigns the address of Sum by adding 200 to its original address",
            "d) Assigns 200 bytes of memory starting the location of Sum"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This basically is used to replace the variable with a constant value. "
    },
    {
        "id": 110,
        "Question": "The purpose of the ORIGIN directive is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To indicate the starting position in memory, where the program block is to be stored",
            "b) To indicate the starting of the computation code",
            "c) To indicate the purpose of the code",
            "d) To list the locations of all the registers used"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This does the function similar to the main statement.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 111,
        "Question": "The directive used to perform initialization before the execution of the code is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reserve",
            "b) Store",
            "c) Dataword",
            "d) EQU"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 112,
        "Question": "_____ directive is used to specify and assign the memory required for the block of code.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Allocate",
            "b) Assign",
            "c) Set",
            "d) Reserve"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: This instruction is used to allocate a block of memory and to store the object code of the program there."
    },
    {
        "id": 113,
        "Question": "_____ directive specifies the end of execution of a program.",
        "Options": [
            "a) End",
            "b) Return",
            "c) Stop",
            "d) Terminate"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This instruction directive is used to terminate the program execution. "
    },
    {
        "id": 114,
        "Question": "The last statement of the source program should be _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stop",
            "b) Return",
            "c) OP",
            "d) End"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: This enables the processor to load some other process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 115,
        "Question": "When dealing with the branching code the assembler ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replaces the target with its address",
            "b) Does not replace until the test condition is satisfied",
            "c) Finds the Branch offset and replaces the Branch target with it",
            "d) Replaces the target with the value specified by the DATAWORD directive"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: When the assembler comes across the branch code, it immediately finds the branch offset and replaces it with it. "
    },
    {
        "id": 116,
        "Question": "The assembler stores all the names and their corresponding values in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Special purpose Register",
            "b) Symbol Table",
            "c) Value map Set",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The table where the assembler stores the variable names along with their corresponding memory locations and values.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 117,
        "Question": "The assembler stores the object code in  ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Main memory",
            "b) Cache",
            "c) RAM",
            "d) Magnetic disk"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: After compiling the object code, the assembler stores it in the magnetic disk and waits for further execution. "
    },
    {
        "id": 118,
        "Question": "The utility program used to bring the object code into memory for execution is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loader",
            "b) Fetcher",
            "c) Extractor",
            "d) Linker"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The program is used to load the program into memory. "
    },
    {
        "id": 119,
        "Question": "To overcome the problems of the assembler in dealing with branching code we use _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interpreter",
            "b) Debugger",
            "c) Op-Assembler",
            "d) Two-pass assembler"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: This creates entries into the symbol table first and then creates the object code. "
    },
    {
        "id": 120,
        "Question": "The return address of the Sub-routine is pointed to by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) IR",
            "b) PC",
            "c) MAR",
            "d) Special memory registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The return address from the subroutine is pointed to by the PC."
    },
    {
        "id": 121,
        "Question": "The location to return to, from the subroutine is stored in _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) TLB",
            "b) PC",
            "c) MAR",
            "d) Link registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The registers store the return address of the routine and is pointed to by the PC.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 122,
        "Question": "What is subroutine nesting?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Having multiple subroutines in a program",
            "b) Using a linking nest statement to put many subroutines under the same name",
            "c) Having one routine call the other",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 123,
        "Question": "The order in which the return addresses are generated and used is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LIFO",
            "b) FIFO",
            "c) Random",
            "d) Highest priority"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: That is the routine called first is returned first. "
    },
    {
        "id": 124,
        "Question": "In case of nested subroutines the return addresses are stored in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) System heap",
            "b) Special memory buffers",
            "c) Processor stack",
            "d) Registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: In this case, there will be more number of return addresses it is stored on the processor stack.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 125,
        "Question": "The appropriate return addresses are obtained with the help of ____ in case of nested routines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAR",
            "b) MDR",
            "c) Buffers",
            "d) Stack-pointers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The pointers are used to point to the location on the stack where the address is stored. "
    },
    {
        "id": 126,
        "Question": "When parameters are being passed on to the subroutines they are stored in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Registers",
            "b) Memory locations",
            "c) Processor stacks",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: In the case of, parameter passing the data can be stored on any of the storage space.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 127,
        "Question": "The most efficient way of handling parameter passing is by using ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) General purpose registers",
            "b) Stacks",
            "c) Memory locations",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: By using general purpose registers for the parameter passing we make the process more efficient.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 128,
        "Question": "The most Flexible way of logging the return addresses of the subroutines is by using _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Registers",
            "b) Stacks",
            "c) Memory locations",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The stacks are used as Logs for return addresses of the subroutines.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 129,
        "Question": "The private work space dedicated to a subroutine is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) System heap",
            "b) Reserve",
            "c) Stack frame",
            "d) Allocation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This work space is where the intermediate values of the subroutines are stored. "
    },
    {
        "id": 130,
        "Question": "If the subroutine exceeds the private space allocated to it then the values are pushed onto _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stack",
            "b) System heap",
            "c) Reserve Space",
            "d) Stack frame"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: If the allocated work space is exceeded then the data is pushed onto the system stack. "
    },
    {
        "id": 131,
        "Question": "______ pointer is used to point to parameters passed or local parameters of the subroutine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stack pointer",
            "b) Frame pointer",
            "c) Parameter register",
            "d) Log register"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This pointer is used to track the current position of the stack being used. "
    },
    {
        "id": 132,
        "Question": "The reserved memory or private space of the subroutine gets deallocated when _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The stop instruction is executed by the routine",
            "b) The pointer reaches the end of the space",
            "c) When the routine’s return statement is executed",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The work space allocated to a subroutine gets deallocated when the routine is completed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 133,
        "Question": "The private space gets allocated to each subroutine when _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The first statement of the routine is executed",
            "b) When the context switch takes place",
            "c) When the routine gets called",
            "d) When the Allocate instruction is executed"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: When the call statement is executed, simultaneously space also gets allocated.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 134,
        "Question": "_____ the most suitable data structure used to store the return addresses in the case of nested subroutines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Heap",
            "b) Stack",
            "c) Queue",
            "d) List"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 135,
        "Question": "In the case of nested subroutines, the stack top is always _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The saved contents of the called sub routine",
            "b) The saved contents of the calling sub routine",
            "c) The return addresses of the called sub routine",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 136,
        "Question": "The stack frame for each subroutine is present in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Main memory",
            "b) System Heap",
            "c) Processor Stack",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The memory for the work space is allocated from the processor stack. "
    },
    {
        "id": 137,
        "Question": "The data structure suitable for scheduling processes is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) List",
            "b) Heap",
            "c) Queue",
            "d) Stack"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The Queue data structure is generally used for scheduling as it is two directional. "
    },
    {
        "id": 138,
        "Question": "The sub-routine service procedure is similar to that of the interrupt service routine in ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Method of context switch",
            "b) Returning",
            "c) Process execution",
            "d) Method of context switch & Process execution"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The  Subroutine service procedure is the same as the interrupt service routine in all aspects, except the fact that interrupt might not be related to the process being executed."
    },
    {
        "id": 139,
        "Question": "In memory-mapped I/O ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The I/O devices and the memory share the same address space",
            "b) The I/O devices have a separate address space",
            "c) The memory and I/O devices have an associated address space",
            "d) A part of the memory is specifically set aside for the I/O operation"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Its the different modes of accessing the i/o devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 140,
        "Question": "The usual BUS structure used to connect the I/O devices is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Star BUS structure",
            "b) Multiple BUS structure",
            "c) Single BUS structure",
            "d) Node to Node BUS structure"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: BUS is a collection of address, control and data lines used to connect the various devices of the computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 141,
        "Question": "The advantage of I/O mapped devices to memory mapped is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The former offers faster transfer of data",
            "b) The devices connected using I/O mapping have a bigger buffer space",
            "c) The devices have to deal with fewer address lines",
            "d) No advantage as such"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This type of access is called as I/O mapped devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 142,
        "Question": "The system is notified of a read or write operation by ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Appending an extra bit of the address",
            "b) Enabling the read or write bits of the devices",
            "c) Raising an appropriate interrupt signal",
            "d) Sending a special signal along the BUS"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: Since the I/O mapped devices have a separate address space the address lines are limited by the amount of the space allocated."
    },
    {
        "id": 143,
        "Question": "To overcome the lag in the operating speeds of the I/O device and the processor we use ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) BUffer spaces",
            "b) Status flags",
            "c) Interrupt signals",
            "d) Exceptions"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: It is necessary for the processor to send a signal intimating the request as either read or write."
    },
    {
        "id": 144,
        "Question": "The method of accessing the I/O devices by repeatedly checking the status flags is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Program-controlled I/O",
            "b) Memory-mapped I/O",
            "c) I/O mapped",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The processor operating is much faster than that of the I/O devices, so by using the status flags the processor need not wait till the I/O operation is done. It can continue with its work until the status flag is set."
    },
    {
        "id": 145,
        "Question": "The method of synchronising the processor with the I/O device in which the device sends a signal when it is ready is?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exceptions",
            "b) Signal handling",
            "c) Interrupts",
            "d) DMA"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: In this method, the processor constantly checks the status flags, and when it finds that the flag is set it performs the appropriate operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 146,
        "Question": "The method which offers higher speeds of I/O transfers is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interrupts",
            "b) Memory mapping",
            "c) Program-controlled I/O",
            "d) DMA"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: This is a method of accessing the I/O devices which gives the complete power to the devices, enabling them to intimate the processor when they’re ready for transfer."
    },
    {
        "id": 147,
        "Question": "The process wherein the processor constantly checks the status flags is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polling",
            "b) Inspection",
            "c) Reviewing",
            "d) Echoing"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: In DMA the I/O devices are directly allowed to interact with the memory without the intervention of the processor and the transfers take place in the form of blocks increasing the speed of operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 148,
        "Question": "The interrupt-request line is a part of the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data line",
            "b) Control line",
            "c) Address line",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The Interrupt-request line is a control line along which the device is allowed to send the interrupt signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 149,
        "Question": "The return address from the interrupt-service routine is stored on the ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) System heap",
            "b) Processor register",
            "c) Processor stack",
            "d) Memory"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The Processor after servicing the interrupts as to load the address of the previous process and this address is stored in the stack."
    },
    {
        "id": 150,
        "Question": "The signal sent to the device from the processor to the device after receiving an interrupt is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interrupt-acknowledge",
            "b) Return signal",
            "c) Service signal",
            "d) Permission signal"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The Processor upon receiving the interrupt should let the device know that its request is received."
    },
    {
        "id": 151,
        "Question": "The time between the receiver of an interrupt and its service is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interrupt delay",
            "b) Interrupt latency",
            "c) Cycle time",
            "d) Switching time"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 152,
        "Question": "Interrupts form an important part of _____ systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Batch processing",
            "b) Multitasking",
            "c) Real-time processing",
            "d) Multi-user"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The delay in servicing of an interrupt happens due to the time is taken for contact switch to take place."
    },
    {
        "id": 153,
        "Question": "The resistor which is attached to the service line is called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Push-down resistor",
            "b) Pull-up resistor",
            "c) Break down resistor",
            "d) Line resistor"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: This forms an important part of the Real time system since if a process arrives with greater priority then it raises an interrupt and the other process is stopped and the interrupt will be serviced."
    },
    {
        "id": 154,
        "Question": "An interrupt that can be temporarily ignored is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vectored interrupt",
            "b) Non-maskable interrupt",
            "c) Maskable interrupt",
            "d) High priority interrupt"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 155,
        "Question": "The 8085 microprocessor responds to the presence of an interrupt ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) As soon as the trap pin becomes ‘LOW’",
            "b) By checking the trap pin for ‘high’ status at the end of each instruction fetch",
            "c) By checking the trap pin for ‘high’ status at the end of execution of each instruction",
            "d) By checking the trap pin for ‘high’ status at regular intervals"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 156,
        "Question": "CPU as two modes privileged and non-privileged. In order to change the mode from privileged to non-privileged.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A hardware interrupt is needed",
            "b) A software interrupt is needed",
            "c) Either hardware or software interrupt is needed",
            "d) A non-privileged instruction (which does not generate an interrupt)is needed"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This resistor is used to pull up the voltage of the interrupt service line."
    },
    {
        "id": 157,
        "Question": "Which interrupt is unmaskable?",
        "Options": [
            "a) RST 5.5",
            "b) RST 7.5",
            "c) TRAP",
            "d) Both RST 5.5 and 7.5"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The maskable interrupts are usually low priority interrupts which can be ignored if a higher priority process is being executed."
    },
    {
        "id": 158,
        "Question": "How can the processor ignore other interrupts when it is servicing one ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) By turning off the interrupt request line",
            "b) By disabling the devices from sending the interrupts",
            "c) BY using edge-triggered request lines",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The 8085 microprocessor are designed to complete the execution of the current instruction and then to service the interrupts."
    },
    {
        "id": 159,
        "Question": "When dealing with multiple devices interrupts, which mechanism is easy to implement?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polling method",
            "b) Vectored interrupts",
            "c) Interrupt nesting",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: In this method, the processor checks the IRQ bits of all the devices, whichever is enabled first that device is serviced."
    },
    {
        "id": 160,
        "Question": "The interrupt servicing mechanism in which the requesting device identifies itself to the processor to be serviced is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Polling",
            "b) Vectored interrupts",
            "c) Interrupt nesting",
            "d) Simultaneous requesting"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 161,
        "Question": "In vectored interrupts, how does the device identify itself to the processor?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By sending its device id",
            "b) By sending the machine code for the interrupt service routine",
            "c) By sending the starting address of the service routine",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: By sending the starting address of the routine the device ids the routine required and thereby identifying itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 162,
        "Question": "The code sent by the device in vectored interrupt is _____ long.",
        "Options": [
            "a) upto 16 bits",
            "b) upto 32 bits",
            "c) upto 24 bits",
            "d) 4-8 bits"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 163,
        "Question": "The starting address sent by the device in vectored interrupt is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Location id",
            "b) Interrupt vector",
            "c) Service location",
            "d) Service id"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 164,
        "Question": "The processor indicates to the devices that it is ready to receive interrupts ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) By enabling the interrupt request line",
            "b) By enabling the IRQ bits",
            "c) By activating the interrupt acknowledge line",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: When the processor activates the acknowledge line the devices send their interrupts to the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 165,
        "Question": "Which table handle stores the addresses of the interrupt handling sub-routines?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interrupt-vector table",
            "b) Vector table",
            "c) Symbol link table",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: In polling, the processor checks each of the devices if they wish to perform data transfer and if they do it performs the particular operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 166,
        "Question": "_________ method is used to establish priority by serially connecting all devices that request an interrupt.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Vectored-interrupting",
            "b) Daisy chain",
            "c) Priority",
            "d) Polling"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 167,
        "Question": "In daisy chaining device 0 will pass the signal only if it has _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interrupt request",
            "b) No interrupt request",
            "c) Both No interrupt and Interrupt request",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 168,
        "Question": "______ interrupt method uses register whose bits are set separately by interrupt signal for each device.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Parallel priority interrupt",
            "b) Serial priority interrupt",
            "c) Daisy chaining",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: In the Daisy chain mechanism, all the devices are connected using a single request line and they’re serviced based on the interrupting device’s priority."
    },
    {
        "id": 169,
        "Question": "______________ register is used for the purpose of controlling the status of each interrupt request in parallel priority interrupt.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mass",
            "b) Mark",
            "c) Make",
            "d) Mask"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: In daisy chaining since there is only one request line and only one acknowledges line, the acknowledge signal passes from device to device until the one with the interrupt is found."
    },
    {
        "id": 170,
        "Question": "The added output of the bits of the interrupt register and the mask register is set as an input of ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Priority decoder",
            "b) Priority encoder",
            "c) Process id encoder",
            "d) Multiplexer"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 171,
        "Question": "Interrupts initiated by an instruction is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Internal",
            "b) External",
            "c) Hardware",
            "d) Software"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 172,
        "Question": "If during the execution of an instruction an exception is raised then __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The instruction is executed and the exception is handled",
            "b) The instruction is halted and the exception is handled",
            "c) The processor completes the execution and saves the data and then handle the exception",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: Since the interrupt was raised during the execution of the instruction, the instruction cannot be executed and the exception is served immediately."
    },
    {
        "id": 173,
        "Question": "_____ is/are types of exceptions.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trap",
            "b) Interrupt",
            "c) System calls",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 174,
        "Question": "The program used to find out errors is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Debugger",
            "b) Compiler",
            "c) Assembler",
            "d) Scanner"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: Debugger is a program used to detect and correct errors in the program."
    },
    {
        "id": 175,
        "Question": "The two facilities provided by the debugger is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Trace points",
            "b) Break points",
            "c) Compile",
            "d) Both Trace and Break points"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The debugger provides us with the two facilities to improve the checking of errors."
    },
    {
        "id": 176,
        "Question": "In trace mode of operation is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The program is interrupted after each detection",
            "b) The program will not be stopped and the errors are sorted out after the complete program is scanned",
            "c) There is no effect on the program, i.e the program is executed without rectification of errors",
            "d) The program is halted only at specific points"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: In trace mode, the program is checked line by line and if errors are detected then exceptions are raised right away."
    },
    {
        "id": 177,
        "Question": "What is the operation in Breakpoint mode?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The program is interrupted after each detection",
            "b) The program will not be stopped and the errors are sorted out after the complete program is scanned",
            "c) There is no effect on the program, i.e the program is executed without rectification of errors",
            "d) The program is halted only at specific points"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The Breakpoint mode of operation allows the program to be halted at only specific locations."
    },
    {
        "id": 178,
        "Question": "What are the different modes of operation of a computer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) User and System mode",
            "b) User and Supervisor mode",
            "c) Supervisor and Trace mode",
            "d) Supervisor, User and Trace mode"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The user programs are in the user mode and the system crucial programs are in the supervisor mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 179,
        "Question": "The instructions which can be run only supervisor mode are?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Non-privileged instructions",
            "b) System instructions",
            "c) Privileged instructions",
            "d) Exception instructions"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: These instructions are those which can are crucial for the system’s performance and hence cannot be adultered by user programs, so is run only in supervisor mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 180,
        "Question": "A privilege exception is raised __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) When a process tries to change the mode of the system",
            "b) When a process tries to change the priority level of the other processes",
            "c) When a process tries to access the memory allocated to other users",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 181,
        "Question": "How is a privilege exception dealt with?",
        "Options": [
            "a) The program is halted and the system switches into supervisor mode and restarts the program execution",
            "b) The Program is stopped and removed from the queue",
            "c) The system switches the mode and starts the execution of a new process",
            "d) The system switches mode and runs the debugger"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 182,
        "Question": "The DMA differs from the interrupt mode by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The involvement of the processor for the operation",
            "b) The method of accessing the I/O devices",
            "c) The amount of data transfer possible",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: DMA is an approach of performing data transfers in bulk between memory and the external device without the intervention of the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 183,
        "Question": "The DMA transfers are performed by a control circuit called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Device interface",
            "b) DMA controller",
            "c) Data controller",
            "d) Overlooker"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The Controller performs the functions that would normally be carried out by the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 184,
        "Question": "In DMA transfers, the required signals and addresses are given by the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor",
            "b) Device drivers",
            "c) DMA controllers",
            "d) The program itself"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The DMA controller acts as a processor for DMA transfers and overlooks the entire process."
    },
    {
        "id": 185,
        "Question": "After the completion of the DMA transfer, the processor is notified by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acknowledge signal",
            "b) Interrupt signal",
            "c) WMFC signal",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The controller raises an interrupt signal to notify the processor that the transfer was complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 186,
        "Question": "The DMA controller has _______ registers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 1"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The Controller uses the registers to store the starting address, word count and the status of the operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 187,
        "Question": "When the R/W bit of the status register of the DMA controller is set to 1.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Read operation is performed",
            "b) Write operation is performed",
            "c) Read & Write operation is performed",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 188,
        "Question": "The controller is connected to the ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor BUS",
            "b) System BUS",
            "c) External BUS",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The controller is directly connected to the system BUS to provide faster transfer of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 189,
        "Question": "The technique whereby the DMA controller steals the access cycles of the processor to operate is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast conning",
            "b) Memory Con",
            "c) Cycle stealing",
            "d) Memory stealing"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The DMA controller can perform operations on two different disks if the appropriate details are known."
    },
    {
        "id": 190,
        "Question": "The technique where the controller is given complete access to main memory is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cycle stealing",
            "b) Memory stealing",
            "c) Memory Con",
            "d) Burst mode"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The controller takes over the processor’s access cycles and performs memory operations."
    },
    {
        "id": 191,
        "Question": "The controller uses _____ to help with the transfers when handling network interfaces.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Input Buffer storage",
            "b) Signal enhancers",
            "c) Bridge circuits",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The controller is given full control of the memory access cycles and can transfer blocks at a faster rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 192,
        "Question": "To overcome the conflict over the possession of the BUS we use ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Optimizers",
            "b) BUS arbitrators",
            "c) Multiple BUS structure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The controller stores the data to transfer in the buffer and then transfers it."
    },
    {
        "id": 193,
        "Question": "The registers of the controller are ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 64 bits",
            "b) 24 bits",
            "c) 32 bits",
            "d) 16 bits"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The BUS arbitrator is used to overcome the contention over the BUS possession."
    },
    {
        "id": 194,
        "Question": "When the process requests for a DMA transfer?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Then the process is temporarily suspended",
            "b) The process continues execution",
            "c) Another process gets executed",
            "d) process is temporarily suspended & Another process gets executed"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 195,
        "Question": "The DMA transfer is initiated by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor",
            "b) The process being executed",
            "c) I/O devices",
            "d) OS"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The process requesting the transfer is paused and the operation is performed, meanwhile another process is run on the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 196,
        "Question": "To resolve the clash over the access of the system BUS we use ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Multiple BUS",
            "b) BUS arbitrator",
            "c) Priority access",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The BUS arbitrator is used to allow a device to access the BUS based on certain parameters."
    },
    {
        "id": 197,
        "Question": "The device which is allowed to initiate data transfers on the BUS at any time is called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) BUS master",
            "b) Processor",
            "c) BUS arbitrator",
            "d) Controller"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The device which is currently accessing the BUS is called as the BUS master."
    },
    {
        "id": 198,
        "Question": "______ BUS arbitration approach uses the involvement of the processor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Centralised arbitration",
            "b) Distributed arbitration",
            "c) Random arbitration",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: In this approach, the processor takes into account the various parameters and assigns the BUS to that device."
    },
    {
        "id": 199,
        "Question": "The circuit used for the request line is a _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open-collector",
            "b) EX-OR circuit",
            "c) Open-drain",
            "d) Nand circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 200,
        "Question": "The Centralised BUS arbitration is similar to ______ interrupt circuit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Priority",
            "b) Parallel",
            "c) Single",
            "d) Daisy chain"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 201,
        "Question": "When the processor receives the request from a device, it responds by sending _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Acknowledge signal",
            "b) BUS grant signal",
            "c) Response signal",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The Grant signal is passed from one device to the other until the device that has requested is found."
    },
    {
        "id": 202,
        "Question": "In Centralised Arbitration ______ is/are is the BUS master.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor",
            "b) DMA controller",
            "c) Device",
            "d) Both Processor and DMA controller"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The BUS master is the one that decides which will get the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 203,
        "Question": "Once the BUS is granted to a device ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It activates the BUS busy line",
            "b) Performs the required operation",
            "c) Raises an interrupt",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The BUS busy activated indicates that the BUS is already allocated to a device and is being used."
    },
    {
        "id": 204,
        "Question": "The BUS busy line is made of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Open-drain circuit",
            "b) Open-collector circuit",
            "c) EX-Or circuit",
            "d) Nor circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 205,
        "Question": "After the device completes its operation _____ assumes the control of the BUS.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Another device",
            "b) Processor",
            "c) Controller",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: After the device completes the operation it releases the BUS and the processor takes over it."
    },
    {
        "id": 206,
        "Question": "The BUS busy line is used __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To indicate the processor is busy",
            "b) To indicate that the BUS master is busy",
            "c) To indicate the BUS is already allocated",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 207,
        "Question": "Distributed arbitration makes use of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) BUS master",
            "b) Processor",
            "c) Arbitrator",
            "d) 4-bit ID"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The device uses a 4bit ID number and based on this the BUS is allocated."
    },
    {
        "id": 208,
        "Question": "In Distributed arbitration, the device requesting the BUS ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asserts the Start arbitration signal",
            "b) Sends an interrupt signal",
            "c) Sends an acknowledge signal",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 209,
        "Question": "How is a device selected in Distributed arbitration?",
        "Options": [
            "a) By NANDing the signals passed on all the 4 lines",
            "b) By ANDing the signals passed on all the 4 lines",
            "c) By ORing the signals passed on all the 4 lines",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The OR output of all the 4 lines is obtained and the device with the larger value is assigned the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 210,
        "Question": "If two devices A and B contesting for the BUS have ID’s 5 and 6 respectively, which device gets the BUS based on the Distributed arbitration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Device A",
            "b) Device B",
            "c) Insufficient information",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The device Id’s of both the devices are passed on the lines and since the value of B is greater after the Or operation it gets the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 211,
        "Question": "The primary function of the BUS is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To connect the various devices to the cpu",
            "b) To provide a path for communication between the processor and other devices",
            "c) To facilitate data transfer between various devices",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The BUS is used to allow the passage of commands and data between cpu and devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 212,
        "Question": "The classification of BUSes into synchronous and asynchronous is based on __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The devices connected to them",
            "b) The type of data transfer",
            "c) The Timing of data transfers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The BUS is classified into different types for the convenience of use and depending on the device."
    },
    {
        "id": 213,
        "Question": "The device which starts data transfer is called __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Master",
            "b) Transactor",
            "c) Distributor",
            "d) Initiator"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The device which starts the data transfer is called an initiator."
    },
    {
        "id": 214,
        "Question": "The device which interacts with the initiator is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Slave",
            "b) Master",
            "c) Responder",
            "d) Friend"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The device which receives the commands from the initiator for data transfer."
    },
    {
        "id": 215,
        "Question": "In synchronous BUS, the devices get the timing signals from __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Timing generator in the device",
            "b) A common clock line",
            "c) Timing signals are not used at all",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The devices receive their timing signals from the clock line of the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 216,
        "Question": "The delays caused in the switching of the timing signals is due to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory access time",
            "b) WMFC",
            "c) Propagation delay",
            "d) Processor delay"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The time taken for the signal to reach the BUS from the device or the circuit accounts for this delay."
    },
    {
        "id": 217,
        "Question": "The time for which the data is to be on the BUS is affected by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Propagation delay of the circuit",
            "b) Setup time of the device",
            "c) Memory access time",
            "d) Propagation delay of the circuit & Setup time of the device"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The time for which the data is held is larger than the time taken for propagation delay and setup time."
    },
    {
        "id": 218,
        "Question": "Which is fed into the BUS first by the initiator?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data",
            "b) Address",
            "c) Commands or controls",
            "d) Address, Commands or controls"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 219,
        "Question": "_____________ signal is used as an acknowledgement signal by the slave in Multiple cycle transfers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Ack signal",
            "b) Slave ready signal",
            "c) Master ready signal",
            "d) Slave received signal"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 220,
        "Question": "The master indicates that the address is loaded onto the BUS, by activating _____ signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MSYN",
            "b) SSYN",
            "c) WMFC",
            "d) INTR"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The signal activated by the master in the asynchronous mode of transmission is used to intimate the slave the required data is on the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 221,
        "Question": "The MSYN signal is initiated __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Soon after the address and commands are loaded",
            "b) Soon after the decoding of the address",
            "c) After the slave gets the commands",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The devices with variable speeds are connected using asynchronous BUS, as the devices share a master-slave relationship."
    },
    {
        "id": 222,
        "Question": "In IBM’s S360/370 systems _____ lines are used to select the I/O devices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCAN in and out",
            "b) Connect",
            "c) Search",
            "d) Peripheral"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This signal is activated by the master to tell the slave that the required commands are on the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 223,
        "Question": "The meter in and out lines are used for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Monitoring the usage of devices",
            "b) Monitoring the amount of data transferred",
            "c) Measure the CPU usage",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The signal is used to scan and connect to input or output devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 224,
        "Question": "MRDC stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory Read Enable",
            "b) Memory Ready Command",
            "c) Memory Re-direct Command",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The line is used to monitor the usage of the device for a process."
    },
    {
        "id": 225,
        "Question": "The BUS that allows I/O, memory and Processor to coexist is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Attributed BUS",
            "b) Processor BUS",
            "c) Backplane BUS",
            "d) External BUS"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The command is used to initiate a read from memory operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 226,
        "Question": "The transmission on the asynchronous BUS is also called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Switch mode transmission",
            "b) Variable transfer",
            "c) Bulk transfer",
            "d) Hand-Shake transmission"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 227,
        "Question": "______ serves as an intermediary between the device and the BUSes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interface circuits",
            "b) Device drivers",
            "c) Buffers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The interface circuits act as a hardware interface between the device and the software side."
    },
    {
        "id": 228,
        "Question": "The side of the interface circuits, that has the data path and the control signals to transfer data between interface and device is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) BUS side",
            "b) Port side",
            "c) Hardwell side",
            "d) Software side"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This side connects the device to the motherboard."
    },
    {
        "id": 229,
        "Question": "What is the interface circuit?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Helps in installing of the software driver for the device",
            "b) Houses the buffer that helps in data transfer",
            "c) Helps in the decoding of the address on the address BUs",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: Once the address is put on the BUS the interface circuit decodes the address and uses the buffer space to transfer data."
    },
    {
        "id": 230,
        "Question": "The parallel mode of communication is not suitable for long devices because of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Timing skew",
            "b) Memory access delay",
            "c) Latency",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: By doing this the interface circuits provide a better interconnection between devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 231,
        "Question": "The status flags required for data transfer is present in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Device",
            "b) Device driver",
            "c) Interface circuit",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 232,
        "Question": "User programmable terminals that combine VDT hardware with built-in microprocessor is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) KIPs",
            "b) Pc",
            "c) Mainframe",
            "d) Intelligent terminals"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The interface circuits generate the required clock signal for the synchronous mode of transfer."
    },
    {
        "id": 233,
        "Question": "Which most popular input device is used today for interactive processing and for the one line entry of data for batch processing?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mouse",
            "b) Magnetic disk",
            "c) Visual display terminal",
            "d) Card punch"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The circuit holds the flags which are required for data transfers."
    },
    {
        "id": 234,
        "Question": "The use of spooler programs or _______ Hardware allows PC operators to do the processing work at the same time a printing operation is in progress.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Registers",
            "b) Memory",
            "c) Buffer",
            "d) CPU"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 235,
        "Question": "______ is used as an intermediate to extend the processor BUS.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bridge",
            "b) Router",
            "c) Connector",
            "d) Gateway"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The bridge circuit is basically used to extend the processor BUS to connect devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 236,
        "Question": "________ is an extension of the processor BUS.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCSI BUS",
            "b) USB",
            "c) PCI BUS",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The PCI BUS is used as an extension of the processor BUS and devices connected to it, is like connected to the Processor itself."
    },
    {
        "id": 237,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ISA?",
        "Options": [
            "a) International American Standard",
            "b) Industry Standard Architecture",
            "c) International Standard Architecture",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The ISA is an architectural standard developed by IBM for its PC’s."
    },
    {
        "id": 238,
        "Question": "What is the full form of ANSI?",
        "Options": [
            "a) American National Standards Institute",
            "b) Architectural National Standards Institute",
            "c) Asian National Standards Institute",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The ANSI is one of the standard architecture used by companies in designing the systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 239,
        "Question": "The video devices are connected to ______ BUS.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI",
            "b) USB",
            "c) HDMI",
            "d) SCSI"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The SCSI BUS is used to connect the video devices to a processor by providing a parallel BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 240,
        "Question": "SCSI stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Signal Computer System Interface",
            "b) Small Computer System Interface",
            "c) Small Coding System Interface",
            "d) Signal Coding System Interface"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The SCSI BUS is used to connect disks and video controllers."
    },
    {
        "id": 241,
        "Question": "ISO stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) International Standards Organisation",
            "b) International Software Organisation",
            "c) Industrial Standards Organisation",
            "d) Industrial Software Organisation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The ISO is yet another architectural standard, used to design systems."
    },
    {
        "id": 242,
        "Question": "The system developed by IBM with ISA architecture is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) SPARC",
            "b) SUN-SPARC",
            "c) PC-AT",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 243,
        "Question": "IDE disk is connected to the PCI BUS using ______ interface.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ISA",
            "b) ISO",
            "c) ANSI",
            "d) IEEE"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 244,
        "Question": "IDE stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrated Device Electronics",
            "b) International Device Encoding",
            "c) Industrial Decoder Electronics",
            "d) International Decoder Encoder"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The IDE interface is used to connect the hard disk to the processor in most of the Pentium processors."
    },
    {
        "id": 245,
        "Question": "The _____ circuit enables the generation of the ASCII code when the key is pressed.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generator",
            "b) Debouncing",
            "c) Encoder",
            "d) Logger"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The signal generated upon the pressing of a button is encoded by the encoder circuit into the corresponding ASCII value."
    },
    {
        "id": 246,
        "Question": "To overcome multiple signals being generated upon a single press of the button, we make use of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Generator circuit",
            "b) Debouncing circuit",
            "c) Multiplexer",
            "d) XOR circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: When the button is pressed, the contact surfaces bounce and hence it might lead to the generation of multiple signals. In order to overcome this, we use Debouncing circuits."
    },
    {
        "id": 247,
        "Question": "The best mode of connection between devices which need to send or receive large amounts of data over a short distance is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) BUS",
            "b) Serial port",
            "c) Parallel port",
            "d) Isochronous port"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The parallel port transfers around 8 to 16 bits of data simultaneously over the lines, hence increasing transfer rates."
    },
    {
        "id": 248,
        "Question": "The output of the encoder circuit is/are ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ASCII code",
            "b) ASCII code and the valid signal",
            "c) Encoded signal",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The encoder outputs the ASCII value along with the valid signal which indicates that a key was pressed."
    },
    {
        "id": 249,
        "Question": "The disadvantage of using a parallel mode of communication is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is costly",
            "b) Leads to erroneous data transfer",
            "c) Security of data",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The parallel mode of data transfer is costly as it involves data being sent over parallel lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 250,
        "Question": "In a 32 bit processor, the A0 bit of the address line is connected to _____ of the parallel port interface.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Valid bit",
            "b) Idle bit",
            "c) Interrupt enable bit",
            "d) Status or data register"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 251,
        "Question": "The Status flag circuit is implemented using _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) RS flip flop",
            "b) D flip flop",
            "c) JK flip flop",
            "d) Xor circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The circuit is implemented using the edge triggered D flip flop, that is triggered on the rising edge of the valid signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 252,
        "Question": "In the output interface of the parallel port, along with the valid signal ______ is also sent.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data",
            "b) Idle signal",
            "c) Interrupt",
            "d) Acknowledge signal"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The idle signal is used to check if the device is idle and ready to receive data."
    },
    {
        "id": 253,
        "Question": "DDR stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data Direction Register",
            "b) Data Decoding Register",
            "c) Data Decoding Rate",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This register is used to control the flow of data from the DATAOUT register."
    },
    {
        "id": 254,
        "Question": "In a general 8-bit parallel interface, the INTR line is connected to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Status and Control unit",
            "b) DDR",
            "c) Register select",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 255,
        "Question": "The mode of transmission of data, where one bit is sent for each clock cycle is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asynchronous",
            "b) Parallel",
            "c) Serial",
            "d) Isochronous"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: In the isochronous mode of transmission, each bit of the data is sent per each cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 256,
        "Question": "The transformation between the Parallel and serial ports is done with the help of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flip flops",
            "b) Logic circuits",
            "c) Shift registers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The Shift registers are used to output the data in the desired format based on the need."
    },
    {
        "id": 257,
        "Question": "The serial port is used to connect basically _____ and processor.",
        "Options": [
            "a) I/O devices",
            "b) Speakers",
            "c) Printer",
            "d) Monitor"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The serial port is used to connect the keyboard and other devices which input or output one bit at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 258,
        "Question": "The double buffer is used for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Enabling retrieval of multiple bits of input",
            "b) Combining the input and output operations",
            "c) Extending the buffer capacity",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 259,
        "Question": "______ to increase the flexibility of the serial ports.",
        "Options": [
            "a) The wires used for ports is changed",
            "b) The ports are made to allow different clock signals for input and output",
            "c) The drivers are modified",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The ports are made more flexible by enabling the input or output of different clock signals for different devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 260,
        "Question": "UART stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Universal Asynchronous Relay Transmission",
            "b) Universal Accumulator Register Transfer",
            "c) Universal Asynchronous Receiver Transmitter",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The UART is a standard developed for designing serial ports."
    },
    {
        "id": 261,
        "Question": "The key feature of UART is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Its architectural design",
            "b) Its simple implementation",
            "c) Its general purpose usage",
            "d) Its enhancement of connecting low speed devices"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 262,
        "Question": "The data transfer in UART is done in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asynchronous start stop format",
            "b) Synchronous start stop format",
            "c) Isochronous format",
            "d) EBDIC format"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: This basically means that the data transfer is done in asynchronous mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 263,
        "Question": "The standard used in serial ports to facilitate communication is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) RS-246",
            "b) RS-LNK",
            "c) RS-232-C",
            "d) Both RS-246 and RS-LNK"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: This is a standard that acts as a protocol for message communication involving serial ports."
    },
    {
        "id": 264,
        "Question": "In a serial port interface, the INTR line is connected to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Status register",
            "b) Shift register",
            "c) Chip select",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 265,
        "Question": "The PCI follows a set of standards primarily used in _____ PC’s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Intel",
            "b) Motorola",
            "c) IBM",
            "d) SUN"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The PCI BUS has a closer resemblance to IBM architecture."
    },
    {
        "id": 266,
        "Question": "The ______ is the BUS used in Macintosh PC’s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) NuBUS",
            "b) EISA",
            "c) PCI",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The NuBUS is an extension of the processor BUS in Macintosh PC’s."
    },
    {
        "id": 267,
        "Question": "The key feature of the PCI BUS is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low cost connectivity",
            "b) Plug and Play capability",
            "c) Expansion of Bandwidth",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The PCI BUS was the first to introduce plug and play interface for I/O devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 268,
        "Question": "PCI stands for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Peripheral Component Interconnect",
            "b) Peripheral Computer Internet",
            "c) Processor Computer Interconnect",
            "d) Processor Cable Interconnect"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The PCI BUS is used as an extension for the processor BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 269,
        "Question": "The PCI BUS supports _____ address space/s.",
        "Options": [
            "a) I/O",
            "b) Memory",
            "c) Configuration",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The PCI BUS is mainly built to provide a wide range of connectivity for devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 270,
        "Question": "______ address space gives the PCI its plug and plays capability.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Configuration",
            "b) I/O",
            "c) Memory",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The configuration address space is used to store the details of the connected device."
    },
    {
        "id": 271,
        "Question": "_____ provides a separate physical connection to the memory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI BUS",
            "b) PCI interface",
            "c) PCI bridge",
            "d) Switch circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The PCI bridge is a circuit that acts as a bridge between the BUS and the memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 272,
        "Question": "The master is also called as _____ in PCI terminology.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initiator",
            "b) Commander",
            "c) Chief",
            "d) Starter"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The address is stored by the slave in a buffer and hence it is not required by the master to hold it."
    },
    {
        "id": 273,
        "Question": "Signals whose names end in ____ are asserted in the low voltage state.",
        "Options": [
            "a) $",
            "b) #",
            "c) *",
            "d) !"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The Master is also called as an initiator in PCI terminology as it is the one that initiates a data transfer."
    },
    {
        "id": 274,
        "Question": "A complete transfer operation over the BUS, involving the address and a burst of data is called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transaction",
            "b) Transfer",
            "c) Move",
            "d) Procedure"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 275,
        "Question": "The device connected to the BUS are given addresses of ____ bit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24",
            "b) 64",
            "c) 32",
            "d) 16"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: Each of the devices connected to the BUS will be allocated an address during the initialization phase."
    },
    {
        "id": 276,
        "Question": "The PCI BUS has _____ interrupt request lines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 4",
            "d) 3"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The interrupt request lines are used by the devices connected to raise the interrupts."
    },
    {
        "id": 277,
        "Question": "_____ signal is sent by the initiator to indicate the duration of the transaction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) FRAME#",
            "b) IRDY#",
            "c) TMY#",
            "d) SELD#"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The FRAME signal is used to indicate the time required by the device."
    },
    {
        "id": 278,
        "Question": "______ signal is used to enable commands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) FRAME#",
            "b) IRDY#",
            "c) TMY#",
            "d) c/BE#"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The signal is used to enable 4 command lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 279,
        "Question": "IRDY# signal is used for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Selecting the interrupt line",
            "b) Sending an interrupt",
            "c) Saying that the initiator is ready",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The initiator transmits this signal to tell the target that it is ready."
    },
    {
        "id": 280,
        "Question": "The signal used to indicate that the slave is ready is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) SLRY#",
            "b) TRDY#",
            "c) DSDY#",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 281,
        "Question": "DEVSEL# signal is used _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To select the device",
            "b) To list all the devices connected",
            "c) By the device to indicate that it is ready for a transaction",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: This is signal is activated by the device after it as recognized the address and commands put on the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 282,
        "Question": "The signal used to initiate device select ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IRDY#",
            "b) S/BE",
            "c) DEVSEL#",
            "d) IDSEL#"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: This signal is used to initialization of device select."
    },
    {
        "id": 283,
        "Question": "The PCi BUS allows us to connect _______ I/O devices.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 21",
            "b) 13",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 11"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The PCI BUS allows only 21 devices to be connected as only the higher order 21 bits of the 32 bit address space is used to specify the device."
    },
    {
        "id": 284,
        "Question": "The key features of the SCSI BUS are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cost effective connective media",
            "b) The ability overlap data transfer requests",
            "c) The highly efficient data transmission",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The SCSI BUS can overlap various data transfer requests by the devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 285,
        "Question": "In a data transfer operation involving SCSI BUS, the control is with ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Initiator",
            "b) Target",
            "c) SCSI controller",
            "d) Target Controller"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The initiator involves in the arbitration process and after winning the BUS it’ll hand over the control to the target controller."
    },
    {
        "id": 286,
        "Question": "What is DB(P) line?",
        "Options": [
            "a) That the data line is carrying the device information",
            "b) That the data line is carrying the parity information",
            "c) That the data line is partly closed",
            "d) That the data line is temporarily occupied"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The processor or the controller is unaware of the data being transferred."
    },
    {
        "id": 287,
        "Question": "The BSY signal signifies _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The BUs is busy",
            "b) The controller is busy",
            "c) The Initiator is busy",
            "d) The Target is Busy"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 288,
        "Question": "The SEL signal signifies _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The initiator is selected",
            "b) The device for BUS control is selected",
            "c) That the target is being selected",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: This signal is generally initiated when the BUS is currently occupied in an operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 289,
        "Question": "________ signal is asserted when the initiator wishes to send a message to the target.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MSG",
            "b) APP",
            "c) SMS",
            "d) ATN"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This signal is usually asserted during the selection or reselection process."
    },
    {
        "id": 290,
        "Question": "The MSG signal is used _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To send a message to the target",
            "b) To receive a message from the mailbox",
            "c) To tell that the information being sent is a message",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The ATN signal is short for attention, which is used to intimate the target that the initiator sent a message to it."
    },
    {
        "id": 291,
        "Question": "_____ is used to reset all the device controls to their startup state.",
        "Options": [
            "a) SRT",
            "b) RST",
            "c) ATN",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 292,
        "Question": "The SCSI BUS uses ______ arbitration.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Distributed",
            "b) Centralised",
            "c) Daisy chain",
            "d) Hybrid"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 293,
        "Question": "SCSI stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Small Computer System Interface",
            "b) Switch Computer system Interface",
            "c) Small Component System Interface",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The SCSI BUS is one of the expansion BUSes used in a system."
    },
    {
        "id": 294,
        "Question": "ANSI stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) American National System Interface",
            "b) ASCII National Standard Interface",
            "c) American Network System Interface",
            "d) American National Standard Institute"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: This a standard for designing BUSes and other system components."
    },
    {
        "id": 295,
        "Question": "A narrow SCSI BUS has _____ data lines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 6",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 16",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The SCSI BUS which is narrow is capable of transferring 8 bits of data at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 296,
        "Question": "Single ended transmission means _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) That all the signals have a similar bit pattern",
            "b) That the signals have a common source",
            "c) That the signals have a common ground return",
            "d) That the signals have a similar voltage signature"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: These type of signals are a common feature of the SCSI BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 297,
        "Question": "HVD stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) High Voltage Differential",
            "b) High Voltage Density",
            "c) High Video Definition",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: This is a type of signaling which uses 5v of current."
    },
    {
        "id": 298,
        "Question": "For better transfer rates on the SCSI BUS the length of the cable is limited to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2m",
            "b) 4m",
            "c) 1.3m",
            "d) 1.6m"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: To increase the transmission rate in SCSI in SE mode of transfer the wire length is restricted to 1.6m."
    },
    {
        "id": 299,
        "Question": "The maximum number of devices that can be connected to SCSI BUS is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 10",
            "c) 16",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 300,
        "Question": "The SCSI BUS is connected to the processor through _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) SCSI Controller",
            "b) Bridge",
            "c) Switch",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: This is used to coordinate and monitor the data transfer over the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 301,
        "Question": "The mode of data transfer used by the controller is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interrupt",
            "b) DMA",
            "c) Asynchronous",
            "d) Synchronous"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 302,
        "Question": "The data is stored on the disk in the form of blocks called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pages",
            "b) Frames",
            "c) Sectors",
            "d) Tables"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The data is stored on the disk in the form of a collection of blocks called as sectors."
    },
    {
        "id": 303,
        "Question": "The transfer rate, when the USB is operating in low-speed of operation is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5 Mb/s",
            "b) 12 Mb/s",
            "c) 2.5 Mb/s",
            "d) 1.5 Mb/s"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The USB has two rates of operation the low-speed and the full-speed one."
    },
    {
        "id": 304,
        "Question": "The high speed mode of operation of the USB was introduced by _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) ISA",
            "b) USB 3.0",
            "c) USB 2.0",
            "d) ANSI"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The high-speed mode of operation was introduced with USB 2.0, which enabled the USB to operate at 480 Mb/s."
    },
    {
        "id": 305,
        "Question": "The sampling process in speaker output is a ________ process.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Asynchronous",
            "b) Synchronous",
            "c) Isochronous",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The isochronous process means each bit of data is separated by a time interval."
    },
    {
        "id": 306,
        "Question": "The USB device follows _______ structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) List",
            "b) Huffman",
            "c) Hash",
            "d) Tree"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The USB has a tree structure with the root hub at the centre."
    },
    {
        "id": 307,
        "Question": "The I/O devices form the _____ of the tree structure.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Leaves",
            "b) Subordinate roots",
            "c) Left subtrees",
            "d) Right subtrees"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The I/o devices form the leaves of the structure."
    },
    {
        "id": 308,
        "Question": "The device can send a message to the host by taking part in _____ for the communication path.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Arbitration",
            "b) Polling",
            "c) Prioritizing",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The USB does a serial mode of data transfer."
    },
    {
        "id": 309,
        "Question": "When the USB is connected to a system, its root hub is connected to the ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI BUS",
            "b) SCSI BUS",
            "c) Processor BUS",
            "d) IDE"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: It allows only the host to communicate with the devices and not between themselves."
    },
    {
        "id": 310,
        "Question": "The devices connected to USB is assigned a ____ address.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 9 bit",
            "b) 16 bit",
            "c) 4 bit",
            "d) 7 bit"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 311,
        "Question": "The initial address of a device just connected to the HUB is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) AHFG890",
            "b) 0000000",
            "c) FFFFFFF",
            "d) 0101010"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The USB’s root is connected to the processor directly using the BUS."
    },
    {
        "id": 312,
        "Question": "Locations in the device to or from which data transfers can take place is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) End points",
            "b) Hosts",
            "c) Source",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: To make it easier for recognition the devices are given 7 bit addresses."
    },
    {
        "id": 313,
        "Question": "A USB pipe is a ______ channel.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Simplex",
            "b) Half-Duplex",
            "c) Full-Duplex",
            "d) Both Simplex and Full-Duplex"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The USB memory space is not under any address spaces and cannot be accessed."
    },
    {
        "id": 314,
        "Question": "The type/s of packets sent by the USB is/are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data",
            "b) Address",
            "c) Control",
            "d) Both Data and Control"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: By standard, the usual address of a new device is zero."
    },
    {
        "id": 315,
        "Question": "The first field of any packet is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) PID",
            "b) ADDR",
            "c) ENDP",
            "d) CRC16"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The PID is the field that is used to identify the device (the device id)."
    },
    {
        "id": 316,
        "Question": "The last field in the packet is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) PID",
            "b) ADDR",
            "c) ENDP",
            "d) CRC"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The fields are transmitted twice, once with the true values and the second time with the complemented values."
    },
    {
        "id": 317,
        "Question": "The CRC bits are computed based on the values of the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) PID",
            "b) ADDR",
            "c) ENDP",
            "d) Both ADDR and ENDP"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The last 5 bits of the packet is used for error checking, that is cyclic redundancy check."
    },
    {
        "id": 318,
        "Question": "The data packets can contain data upto ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 512 bytes",
            "b) 256 bytes",
            "c) 1024 bytes",
            "d) 2 KB"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The CRC bits are calculated based on the values of the address and endp."
    },
    {
        "id": 319,
        "Question": "The most important objective of the USB is to provide ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Isochronous transmission",
            "b) Plug and play",
            "c) Easy device connection",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 320,
        "Question": "The transmission over the USB is divided into ____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frames",
            "b) Pages",
            "c) Packets",
            "d) Tokens"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The above are all the common features of the USB."
    },
    {
        "id": 321,
        "Question": "The _____ signal is used to indicate the beginning of a new frame.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Start",
            "b) SOF",
            "c) BEG",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: To support the isochronous mode of operation the usb transmission is divided into frames."
    },
    {
        "id": 322,
        "Question": "The SOF is transmitted every ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1s",
            "b) 5s",
            "c) 1ms",
            "d) 1Us"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The SOF(State Of Frame) is used to indicate the beginning of a new frame."
    },
    {
        "id": 323,
        "Question": "The power specification of usb is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5v",
            "b) 10v",
            "c) 24v",
            "d) 10v"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 324,
        "Question": "The duration between the read and the mfc signal is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Access time",
            "b) Latency",
            "c) Delay",
            "d) Cycle time"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The time between the issue of a read signal and the completion of it is called memory access time."
    },
    {
        "id": 325,
        "Question": "The minimum time delay between two successive memory read operations is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cycle time",
            "b) Latency",
            "c) Delay",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The Time taken by the cpu to end one read operation and to start one more is cycle time."
    },
    {
        "id": 326,
        "Question": "MFC is used to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Issue a read signal",
            "b) Signal to the device that the memory read operation is complete",
            "c) Signal the processor the memory operation is complete",
            "d) Assign a device to perform the read operation"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The MFC stands for memory Function Complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 327,
        "Question": "__________ is the bottleneck, when it comes computer performance.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory access time",
            "b) Memory cycle time",
            "c) Delay",
            "d) Latency"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The processor can execute instructions faster than they’re fetched, hence cycle time is the bottleneck for performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 328,
        "Question": "The logical addresses generated by the cpu are mapped onto physical memory by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Relocation register",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) MMU",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The MMU stands for memory management unit, which is used to map logical address onto the physical address."
    },
    {
        "id": 329,
        "Question": "VLSI stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very Large Scale Integration",
            "b) Very Large Stand-alone Integration",
            "c) Volatile Layer System Interface",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 330,
        "Question": "The cells in a row are connected to a common line called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Work line",
            "b) Word line",
            "c) Length line",
            "d) Principle diagonal"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This means that the cell contents together form one word of instruction or data."
    },
    {
        "id": 331,
        "Question": "The cells in each column are connected to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Word line",
            "b) Data line",
            "c) Read line",
            "d) Sense/ Write line"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The cells in each column are connected to the sense/write circuit using two bit lines and which is in turn connected to the data lines."
    },
    {
        "id": 332,
        "Question": "The word line is driven by the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chip select",
            "b) Address decoder",
            "c) Data line",
            "d) Control line"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 333,
        "Question": "A 16 X 8 Organisation of memory cells, can store upto _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 256 bits",
            "b) 1024 bits",
            "c) 512 bits",
            "d) 128 bits"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: It can store upto 128 bits as each cell can hold one bit of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 334,
        "Question": "A memory organisation that can hold upto 1024 bits and has a minimum of 10 address lines can be organized into _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 128 X 8",
            "b) 256 X 4",
            "c) 512 X 2",
            "d) 1024 X 1"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: All the others require less than 10 address bits."
    },
    {
        "id": 335,
        "Question": "Circuits that can hold their state as long as power is applied is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dynamic memory",
            "b) Static memory",
            "c) Register",
            "d) Cache"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 336,
        "Question": "The number of external connections required in 16 X 8 memory organisation is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) 14",
            "b) 19",
            "c) 15",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: In the 14, 8-data lines,4-address lines and 2 are sense/write and CS signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 337,
        "Question": "The advantage of CMOS SRAM over the transistor one’s is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low cost",
            "b) High efficiency",
            "c) High durability",
            "d) Low power consumption"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: This is because the cell consumes power only when it is being accessed."
    },
    {
        "id": 338,
        "Question": "In a 4M-bit chip organisation has a total of 19 external connections.then it has _______ address if 8 data lines are there.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 12"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: To have 8 data lines and 19 external connections it has to have 9 address lines(i.e 512 x 8 organisation)."
    },
    {
        "id": 339,
        "Question": "The Reason for the disregarding of the SRAM’s is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low Efficiency",
            "b) High power consumption",
            "c) High Cost",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The reason for the high cost of the SRAM is because of the usage of more number of transistors."
    },
    {
        "id": 340,
        "Question": "The disadvantage of DRAM over SRAM is/are _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lower data storage capacities",
            "b) Higher heat dissipation",
            "c) The cells are not static",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: This means that the cells won’t hold their state indefinitely."
    },
    {
        "id": 341,
        "Question": "The reason for the cells to lose their state over time is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The lower voltage levels",
            "b) Usage of capacitors to store the charge",
            "c) Use of Shift registers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: Since capacitors are used the charge dissipates over time."
    },
    {
        "id": 342,
        "Question": "The capacitors lose the charge over time due to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The leakage resistance of the capacitor",
            "b) The small current in the transistor after being turned on",
            "c) The defect of the capacitor",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The capacitor loses charge due to the backward current of the transistor and due to the small resistance."
    },
    {
        "id": 343,
        "Question": "_________ circuit is used to restore the capacitor value.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sense amplify",
            "b) Signal amplifier",
            "c) Delta modulator",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The sense amplifier detects if the value is above or below the threshold and then restores it."
    },
    {
        "id": 344,
        "Question": "To reduce the number of external connections required, we make use of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) De-multiplexer",
            "b) Multiplexer",
            "c) Encoder",
            "d) Decoder"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: We multiplex the various address lines onto fewer pins."
    },
    {
        "id": 345,
        "Question": "The processor must take into account the delay in accessing the memory location, such memories are called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay integrated",
            "b) Asynchronous memories",
            "c) Synchronous memories",
            "d) Isochronous memories"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 346,
        "Question": "To get the row address of the required data ______ is enabled.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CAS",
            "b) RAS",
            "c) CS",
            "d) Sense/write"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This makes the contents of the row required refreshed."
    },
    {
        "id": 347,
        "Question": "In order to read multiple bytes of a row at the same time, we make use of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Latch",
            "b) Shift register",
            "c) Cache",
            "d) Memory extension"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The latch makes it easy to ready multiple bytes of data of the same row simultaneously by just giving the consecutive column address."
    },
    {
        "id": 348,
        "Question": "The block transfer capability of the DRAM is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Burst mode",
            "b) Block mode",
            "c) Fast page mode",
            "d) Fast frame mode"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 349,
        "Question": "The difference between DRAM’s and SDRAM’s is/are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The DRAM’s will not use the master slave relationship in data transfer",
            "b) The SDRAM’s make use of clock",
            "c) The SDRAM’s are more power efficient",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The SDRAM’s make use of clock signals to synchronize their operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 350,
        "Question": "The difference in the address and data connection between DRAM’s and SDRAM’s is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The usage of more number of pins in SDRAM’s",
            "b) The requirement of more address lines in SDRAM’s",
            "c) The usage of a buffer in SDRAM’s",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The SDRAM uses buffered storage of address and data."
    },
    {
        "id": 351,
        "Question": "A _______ is used to restore the contents of the cells.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sense amplifier",
            "b) Refresh counter",
            "c) Restorer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The Counter helps to restore the charge on the capacitor."
    },
    {
        "id": 352,
        "Question": "The mode register is used to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Select the row or column data transfer mode",
            "b) Select the mode of operation",
            "c) Select mode of storing the data",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The mode register is used to choose between burst mode or bit mode of operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 353,
        "Question": "The time taken to transfer a word of data to or from the memory is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Access time",
            "b) Cycle time",
            "c) Memory latency",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 354,
        "Question": "The SDRAM performs operation on the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Rising edge of the clock",
            "b) Falling edge of the clock",
            "c) Middle state of the clock",
            "d) Transition state of the clock"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The performance of the memory is measured by means of latency."
    },
    {
        "id": 355,
        "Question": "DDR SDRAM’s perform faster data transfer by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrating the hardware",
            "b) Transferring on both edges",
            "c) Improving the clock speeds",
            "d) Increasing the bandwidth"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: In SDRAM’s all the bytes of data to be read or written are stored in the buffer until the operation is complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 356,
        "Question": "To improve the data retrieval rate ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The memory is divided into two banks",
            "b) The hardware is changed",
            "c) The clock frequency is increased",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The SDRAM’s are edge-triggered."
    },
    {
        "id": 357,
        "Question": "The chip can be disabled or cut off from an external connection using ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Chip select",
            "b) LOCK",
            "c) ACPT",
            "d) RESET"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The chip gets enabled if the CS is set otherwise the chip gets disabled."
    },
    {
        "id": 358,
        "Question": "To organise large memory chips we make use of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Integrated chips",
            "b) Upgraded hardware",
            "c) Memory modules",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The cell blocks are arranged and put in a memory module."
    },
    {
        "id": 359,
        "Question": "The less space consideration as lead to the development of ________ (for large memories).",
        "Options": [
            "a) SIMM’s",
            "b) DIMS’s",
            "c) SRAM’s",
            "d) Both SIMM’s and DIMS’s"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The SIMM (single inline memory module) or DIMM (dual inline memory module) occupy less space while providing greater memory space."
    },
    {
        "id": 360,
        "Question": "The SRAM’s are basically used as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Registers",
            "b) Caches",
            "c) TLB",
            "d) Buffer"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The SRAM’s are used as caches as their operation speed is very high."
    },
    {
        "id": 361,
        "Question": "The higher order bits of the address are used to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Specify the row address",
            "b) Specify the column address",
            "c) Input the CS",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 362,
        "Question": "The address lines multiplexing is done using ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMU",
            "b) Memory controller unit",
            "c) Page table",
            "d) Overlay generator"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This unit multiplexes the various address lines to lesser pins on the chip."
    },
    {
        "id": 363,
        "Question": "The controller multiplexes the addresses after getting the _____ signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) INTR",
            "b) ACK",
            "c) RESET",
            "d) Request"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The controller gets the request from the device needing the memory read or write operation and then it multiplexes the address."
    },
    {
        "id": 364,
        "Question": "The RAS and CAS signals are provided by the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Mode register",
            "b) CS",
            "c) Memory controller",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The multiplexed signal of the controller is split into RAS and CAS."
    },
    {
        "id": 365,
        "Question": "Consider a memory organised into 8K rows, and that it takes 4 cycles to complete a read operation. Then the refresh overhead of the chip is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0.0021",
            "b) 0.0038",
            "c) 0.0064",
            "d) 0.0128"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The refresh overhead is calculated by taking into account the total time for refreshing and the interval of each refresh."
    },
    {
        "id": 366,
        "Question": "RAMBUS is better than the other memory chips in terms of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Efficiency",
            "b) Speed of operation",
            "c) Wider bandwidth",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The RAMBUS is much advanced mode of memory storage."
    },
    {
        "id": 367,
        "Question": "The key feature of the RAMBUS tech is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Greater memory utilisation",
            "b) Efficiency",
            "c) Speed of transfer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The RAMBUS was developed basically to lessen the data transfer time."
    },
    {
        "id": 368,
        "Question": "The increase in operation speed is done by ________________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reducing the reference voltage",
            "b) Increasing the clk frequency",
            "c) Using enhanced hardware",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The reference voltage is reduced from the Vsupply about 2v."
    },
    {
        "id": 369,
        "Question": "The data is transferred over the RAMBUS as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Packets",
            "b) Blocks",
            "c) Swing voltages",
            "d) Bits"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: By using voltage swings to transfer data, the transfer rate along with efficiency is improved."
    },
    {
        "id": 370,
        "Question": "The type of signaling used in RAMBUS is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) CLK signaling",
            "b) Differential signaling",
            "c) Integral signaling",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The differential signaling basically means using voltage swings to transmit data."
    },
    {
        "id": 371,
        "Question": "The special communication used in RAMBUS are _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAMBUS channel",
            "b) D-link",
            "c) Dial-up",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The special communication link is used to provide the necessary design and required hardware for the transmission."
    },
    {
        "id": 372,
        "Question": "The original design of the RAMBUS required for ________ data lines.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 6",
            "c) 8",
            "d) 9"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: Out of the 9 data lines, 8 were used for data transmission and the one left was used for parity checking."
    },
    {
        "id": 373,
        "Question": "The RAMBUS requires specially designed memory chips similar to _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) SRAM",
            "b) SDRAM",
            "c) DRAM",
            "d) DDRRAM"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The special memory chip should be able to transmit data on both the edges and is called as RDRAM’s."
    },
    {
        "id": 374,
        "Question": "A RAMBUS which has 18 data lines is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Extended RAMBUS",
            "b) Direct RAMBUS",
            "c) Multiple RAMBUS",
            "d) Indirect RAMBUS"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: The direct RAMBUS is used to transmit 2 bytes of data at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 375,
        "Question": "The RDRAM chips assembled into larger memory modules called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) RRIM",
            "b) DIMM",
            "c) SIMM",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 376,
        "Question": "PROM stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Programmable Read Only Memory",
            "b) Pre-fed Read Only Memory",
            "c) Pre-required Read Only Memory",
            "d) Programmed Read Only Memory"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: If the gate of the transistor is closed then, the value of zero is stored in the ROM."
    },
    {
        "id": 377,
        "Question": "The PROM is more effective than ROM chips in regard to _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost",
            "b) Memory management",
            "c) Speed of operation",
            "d) Both Cost and Speed of operation"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: It allows the user to program the ROM."
    },
    {
        "id": 378,
        "Question": "The difference between the EPROM and ROM circuitry is _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) The usage of MOSFET’s over transistors",
            "b) The usage of JFET’s over transistors",
            "c) The usage of an extra transistor",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The PROM is cheaper than ROM as they can be programmed manually."
    },
    {
        "id": 379,
        "Question": "The ROM chips are mainly used to store _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) System files",
            "b) Root directories",
            "c) Boot files",
            "d) Driver files"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The EPROM uses an extra transistor where the ground connection is there in the ROM chip."
    },
    {
        "id": 380,
        "Question": "The contents of the EPROM are erased by ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Overcharging the chip",
            "b) Exposing the chip to UV rays",
            "c) Exposing the chip to IR rays",
            "d) Discharging the Chip"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The ROM chips are used to store boot files required for the system startup."
    },
    {
        "id": 381,
        "Question": "The disadvantage of the EPROM chip is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) The high cost factor",
            "b) The low efficiency",
            "c) The low speed of operation",
            "d) The need to remove the chip physically to reprogram it"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: To erase the contents of the EPROM the chip is exposed to the UV rays, which dissipate the charge on the transistor."
    },
    {
        "id": 382,
        "Question": "The disadvantage of the EEPROM is/are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The requirement of different voltages to read, write and store information",
            "b) The Latency read operation",
            "c) The inefficient memory mapping schemes used",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 383,
        "Question": "The memory devices which are similar to EEPROM but differ in the cost effectiveness is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory sticks",
            "b) Blue-ray devices",
            "c) Flash memory",
            "d) CMOS"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: The disadvantages of the EPROM led to the development of the EEPROM."
    },
    {
        "id": 384,
        "Question": "The flash memories find application in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Super computers",
            "b) Mainframe systems",
            "c) Distributed systems",
            "d) Portable devices"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 385,
        "Question": "The memory module obtained by placing a number of flash chips for higher memory storage called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) FIMM",
            "b) SIMM",
            "c) Flash card",
            "d) RIMM"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The flash memory functions similar to the EEPROM but is much cheaper."
    },
    {
        "id": 386,
        "Question": "The flash memory modules designed to replace the functioning of a hard disk is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) RIMM",
            "b) Flash drives",
            "c) FIMM",
            "d) DIMM"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: This is not permitted as the previous contents of the cells will be overwritten."
    },
    {
        "id": 387,
        "Question": "The reason for the fast operating speeds of the flash drives is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The absence of any movable parts",
            "b) The integrated electronic hardware",
            "c) The improved bandwidth connection",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The flash memories low power requirement enables them to be used in a wide range of hand held devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 388,
        "Question": "The standard SRAM chips are costly as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) They use highly advanced micro-electronic devices",
            "b) They house 6 transistor per chip",
            "c) They require specially designed PCB’s",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: As they require a large number of transistors, their cost per bit increases."
    },
    {
        "id": 389,
        "Question": "The drawback of building a large memory with DRAM is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The large cost factor",
            "b) The inefficient memory organisation",
            "c) The Slow speed of operation",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: c\nExplanation: The DRAM’s were used for large memory modules for a long time until a substitute was found."
    },
    {
        "id": 390,
        "Question": "The fastest data access is provided using _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Caches",
            "b) DRAM’s",
            "c) SRAM’s",
            "d) Registers"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: To improve the speed we use flash drives at the cost of memory space."
    },
    {
        "id": 391,
        "Question": "The memory which is used to store the copy of data or instructions stored in larger memories, inside the CPU is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Level 1 cache",
            "b) Level 2 cache",
            "c) Registers",
            "d) TLB"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: The fastest data access is provided using registers as these memory locations are situated inside the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 392,
        "Question": "The larger memory placed between the primary cache and the memory is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Level 1 cache",
            "b) Level 2 cache",
            "c) EEPROM",
            "d) TLB"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: a\nExplanation: These memory devices are generally used to map onto the data stored in the larger memories."
    },
    {
        "id": 393,
        "Question": "The next level of memory hierarchy after the L2 cache is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary storage",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) Main memory",
            "d) Register"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: b\nExplanation: This is basically used to provide effective memory mapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 394,
        "Question": "The last on the hierarchy scale of memory devices is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Main memory",
            "b) Secondary memory",
            "c) TLB",
            "d) Flash drives"
        ],
        "Answer": " Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 395,
        "Question": "The reason for the implementation of the cache memory is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To increase the internal memory of the system",
            "b) The difference in speeds of operation of the processor and memory",
            "c) To reduce the memory access and cycle time",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This difference in the speeds of operation of the system caused it to be inefficient."
    },
    {
        "id": 396,
        "Question": "The effectiveness of the cache memory is based on the property of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Locality of reference",
            "b) Memory localisation",
            "c) Memory size",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This means that the cache depends on the location in the memory that is referenced often."
    },
    {
        "id": 397,
        "Question": "The temporal aspect of the locality of reference means ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) That the recently executed instruction won’t be executed soon",
            "b) That the recently executed instruction is temporarily not referenced",
            "c) That the recently executed instruction will be executed soon again",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 398,
        "Question": "The spatial aspect of the locality of reference means ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) That the recently executed instruction is executed again next",
            "b) That the recently executed won’t be executed again",
            "c) That the instruction executed will be executed at a later time",
            "d) That the instruction in close proximity of the instruction executed will be executed in future"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The spatial aspect of locality of reference tells that the nearby instruction is more likely to be executed in future."
    },
    {
        "id": 399,
        "Question": "The correspondence between the main memory blocks and those in the cache is given by _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hash function",
            "b) Mapping function",
            "c) Locale function",
            "d) Assign function"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The mapping function is used to map the contents of the memory to the cache."
    },
    {
        "id": 400,
        "Question": "The algorithm to remove and place new contents into the cache is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Replacement algorithm",
            "b) Renewal algorithm",
            "c) Updation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: As the cache gets full, older contents of the cache are swapped out with newer contents. This decision is taken by the algorithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 401,
        "Question": "The write-through procedure is used ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To write onto the memory directly",
            "b) To write and read from memory simultaneously",
            "c) To write directly on the memory and the cache simultaneously",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: When write operation is issued then the corresponding operation is performed."
    },
    {
        "id": 402,
        "Question": "The bit used to signify that the cache location is updated is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dirty bit",
            "b) Update bit",
            "c) Reference bit",
            "d) Flag bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: When the cache location is updated in order to signal to the processor this bit is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 403,
        "Question": "The copy-back protocol is used ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To copy the contents of the memory onto the cache",
            "b) To update the contents of the memory from the cache",
            "c) To remove the contents of the cache and push it on to the memory",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This is another way of performing the write operation, wherein the cache is updated first and then the memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 404,
        "Question": "The approach where the memory contents are transferred directly to the processor from the memory is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Read-later",
            "b) Read-through",
            "c) Early-start",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 405,
        "Question": "The memory blocks are mapped on to the cache with the help of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hash functions",
            "b) Vectors",
            "c) Mapping functions",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The mapping functions are used to map the memory blocks on to their corresponding cache block."
    },
    {
        "id": 406,
        "Question": "During a write operation if the required block is not present in the cache then ______ occurs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Write latency",
            "b) Write hit",
            "c) Write delay",
            "d) Write miss"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: This indicates that the operation has missed and it brings the required block into the cache."
    },
    {
        "id": 407,
        "Question": "In ________ protocol the information is directly written into the main memory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Write through",
            "b) Write back",
            "c) Write first",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In case of the miss, then the data gets written directly in main memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 408,
        "Question": "The only draw back of using the early start protocol is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Time delay",
            "b) Complexity of circuit",
            "c) Latency",
            "d) High miss rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In this protocol, the required block is read and directly sent to the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 409,
        "Question": "The method of mapping the consecutive memory blocks to consecutive cache blocks is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Set associative",
            "b) Associative",
            "c) Direct",
            "d) Indirect"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This method is most simple to implement as it involves direct mapping of memory blocks."
    },
    {
        "id": 410,
        "Question": "While using the direct mapping technique, in a 16 bit system the higher order 5 bits are used for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tag",
            "b) Block",
            "c) Word",
            "d) Id"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The tag is used to identify the block mapped onto one particular cache block."
    },
    {
        "id": 411,
        "Question": "In associative mapping, in a 16 bit system the tag field has ______ bits.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 12",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 9",
            "d) 10"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The tag field is used to check the presence of a mem block."
    },
    {
        "id": 412,
        "Question": "The technique of searching for a block by going through all the tags is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Linear search",
            "b) Binary search",
            "c) Associative search",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The Tag field is used as an id for the different memory blocks mapped to the cache."
    },
    {
        "id": 413,
        "Question": "In set-associative technique, the blocks are grouped into ______ sets.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 12",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In associative mapping, all the tags have to be searched to find the block."
    },
    {
        "id": 414,
        "Question": "A control bit called _________ has to be provided to each block in set-associative.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Idol bit",
            "b) Valid bit",
            "c) Reference bit",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 415,
        "Question": "The bit used to indicate whether the block was recently used or not is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Idol bit",
            "b) Control bit",
            "c) Reference bit",
            "d) Dirty bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The combination of the efficiency of the associative method and the cheapness of the direct mapping, we get the set-associative mapping."
    },
    {
        "id": 416,
        "Question": "Data which is not up-to date is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Spoilt data",
            "b) Stale data",
            "c) Dirty data",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The set-associative technique groups the blocks into different sets."
    },
    {
        "id": 417,
        "Question": "The main memory is structured into modules each with its own address register called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ABR",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) PC",
            "d) IR"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: ABR stands for Address Buffer Register."
    },
    {
        "id": 418,
        "Question": "In memory interleaving, the lower order bits of the address is used to _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Get the data",
            "b) Get the address of the module",
            "c) Get the address of the data within the module",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In a modular approach to memory structuring only one module can be accessed at a time."
    },
    {
        "id": 419,
        "Question": "The number successful accesses to memory stated as a fraction is called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hit rate",
            "b) Miss rate",
            "c) Success rate",
            "d) Access rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: To implement parallelism in data access we use interleaving."
    },
    {
        "id": 420,
        "Question": "The number failed attempts to access memory, stated in the form of a fraction is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hit rate",
            "b) Miss rate",
            "c) Failure rate",
            "d) Delay rate"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The hit rate is an important factor in performance measurement."
    },
    {
        "id": 421,
        "Question": "In associative mapping during LRU, the counter of the new block is set to ‘0’ and all the others are incremented by one, when _____ occurs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay",
            "b) Miss",
            "c) Hit",
            "d) Delayed hit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The miss rate is a key factor in deciding the type of replacement algorithm."
    },
    {
        "id": 422,
        "Question": "In LRU, the referenced blocks counter is set to’0′ and that of the previous blocks are incremented by one and others remain same, in the case of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hit",
            "b) Miss",
            "c) Delay",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Miss usually occurs when the memory block required is not present in the cache."
    },
    {
        "id": 423,
        "Question": "The extra time needed to bring the data into memory in case of a miss is called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay",
            "b) Propagation time",
            "c) Miss penalty",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: If the referenced block is present in the memory it is called as hit."
    },
    {
        "id": 424,
        "Question": "The CPU is also called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor hub",
            "b) ISP",
            "c) Controller",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: ISP stands for Instruction Set Processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 425,
        "Question": "The PC gets incremented _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) After the instruction decoding",
            "b) After the IR instruction gets executed",
            "c) After the fetch cycle",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: By parallelly accessing data we can have a pipelined processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 426,
        "Question": "Which register in the processor is single directional?",
        "Options": [
            "a) MAR",
            "b) MDR",
            "c) PC",
            "d) Temp"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The PC always points to the next instruction to be executed."
    },
    {
        "id": 427,
        "Question": "The transparent register/s is/are __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y",
            "b) Z",
            "c) Temp",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The MAR is single directional as it just takes the address from the processor bus and passes it to the external bus."
    },
    {
        "id": 428,
        "Question": "Which register is connected to the MUX?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Y",
            "b) Z",
            "c) R0",
            "d) Temp"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: These registers are usually used to store temporary values."
    },
    {
        "id": 429,
        "Question": "The registers, ALU and the interconnecting path together are called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control path",
            "b) Flow path",
            "c) Data path",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The MUX can either read the operand from the Y register or increment the PC."
    },
    {
        "id": 430,
        "Question": "The input and output of the registers are governed by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transistors",
            "b) Diodes",
            "c) Gates",
            "d) Switches"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 431,
        "Question": "When two or more clock cycles are used to complete data transfer it is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single phase clocking",
            "b) Multi-phase clocking",
            "c) Edge triggered clocking",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 432,
        "Question": "________ signal is used to show complete of memory operation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MFC",
            "b) WMFC",
            "c) CFC",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This is basically used in systems without edge-triggered flip flops."
    },
    {
        "id": 433,
        "Question": "The completion of the memory operation is indicated using ______ signal.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MFC",
            "b) WMFC",
            "c) CFC",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the gate transfer notation, which indicates the usage of switches to control the flow of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 434,
        "Question": "_________ signal enables the processor to wait for the memory operation to complete.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MFC",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) WMFC",
            "d) ALB"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: MFC stands for Memory Function Complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 435,
        "Question": "The small extremely fast RAM is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cache",
            "b) Heaps",
            "c) Accumulators",
            "d) Stacks"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This signal stands for Wait For Memory Function Complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 436,
        "Question": "The main virtue for using a single Bus structure is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast data transfers",
            "b) Cost-effective connectivity and speed",
            "c) Cost-effective connectivity and ease of attaching peripheral devices",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: A cache speeds up the execution of a program significantly, by keeping a copy of data and instructions locally in the CPU."
    },
    {
        "id": 437,
        "Question": "To extend the connectivity of the processor bus we use ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI bus",
            "b) SCSI bus",
            "c) Controllers",
            "d) Multiple buses"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The advantage of single bus architecture is the simplicity of the design wherein all the components will fit on the same bus and hence it’s cost-effective. It may not be very fast though."
    },
    {
        "id": 438,
        "Question": "The bus used to connect the monitor to the CPU is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI bus",
            "b) SCSI bus",
            "c) Memory bus",
            "d) Rambus"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The PCI bus is generally the system bus on the motherboard and it is used to connect the CPU, Memory, and peripheral devices using other buses or channels or controllers."
    },
    {
        "id": 439,
        "Question": "The IDE bus is used to connect ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAM and processor",
            "b) GPU and processor",
            "c) Both Harddisk and CD/DVD drives and Processor",
            "d) Only CD/DVD drives and Processor"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: PCI bus connects CPU to the Display Unit whereas SCSI bus is used to connect to storage devices."
    },
    {
        "id": 440,
        "Question": "ANSI stands for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) American National Standards Institute",
            "b) American National Standard Interface",
            "c) American Network Standard Interfacing",
            "d) American Network Security Interrupt"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: IDE bus is used to connect to peripheral devices like hard disks and CD/DVD drives using master-slave mode."
    },
    {
        "id": 441,
        "Question": "IBM developed a bus standard for their line of computers ‘PC-AT’ called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IB bus",
            "b) M-bus",
            "c) ISA",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: American National Standards Institute or ANSI is one of the prime organizations in the US which works towards the standardization of various Technologies in Computer-Sciences and other technology fields."
    },
    {
        "id": 442,
        "Question": "The general purpose registers are combined into a block called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Register bank",
            "b) Register Case",
            "c) Register file",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: To make the access of the registers easier, we classify them into register files."
    },
    {
        "id": 443,
        "Question": "In ______ technology, the implementation of the register file is by using an array of memory locations.",
        "Options": [
            "a) VLSI",
            "b) ANSI",
            "c) ISA",
            "d) ASCI"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: By doing so the access of the registers can be made faster."
    },
    {
        "id": 444,
        "Question": "In a three BUS architecture, how many input and output ports are there?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 output and 2 input",
            "b) 1 output and 2 input",
            "c) 2 output and 1 input",
            "d) 1 output and 1 input"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: That is enabling reading from two locations and writing into one."
    },
    {
        "id": 445,
        "Question": "The main advantage of multiple bus organisation over a single bus is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduction in the number of cycles for execution",
            "b) Increase in size of the registers",
            "c) Better Connectivity",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: We have assumed the names of the three BUSes have A, B and C."
    },
    {
        "id": 446,
        "Question": "CISC stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Complete Instruction Sequential Compilation",
            "b) Computer Integrated Sequential Compiler",
            "c) Complex Instruction Set Computer",
            "d) Complex Instruction Sequential Compilation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 447,
        "Question": "If the instruction Add R1, R2, R3 is executed in a system which is pipelined, then the value of S is (Where S is term of the Basic performance equation).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) ~2",
            "c) ~1",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The CISC machines are well adept at handling multiple BUS organisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 448,
        "Question": "In multiple BUS organisation __________ is used to select any of the BUSes for input into ALU.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MUX",
            "b) DE-MUX",
            "c) En-CDS",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The value will be much lower in case of multiple BUS organisation."
    },
    {
        "id": 449,
        "Question": "________ are the different type/s of generating control signals.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro-programmed",
            "b) Hardwired",
            "c) Micro-instruction",
            "d) Both Micro-programmed and Hardwired"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The above is used to generate control signals in different types of system architectures."
    },
    {
        "id": 450,
        "Question": "The type of control signal is generated based on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) contents of the step counter",
            "b) Contents of IR",
            "c) Contents of condition flags",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: Based on the information above the type of control signal is decided."
    },
    {
        "id": 451,
        "Question": "What does the hardwired control generator consist of?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Decoder/encoder",
            "b) Condition codes",
            "c) Control step counter",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The CU uses the above blocks and IR to produce the necessary signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 452,
        "Question": "What does the end instruction do?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It ends the generation of a signal",
            "b) It ends the complete generation process",
            "c) It starts a new instruction fetch cycle and resets the counter",
            "d) It is used to shift the control to the processor"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: It is basically used to start the generation of a new signal."
    },
    {
        "id": 453,
        "Question": "What does the RUN signal do?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It causes the termination of a signal",
            "b) It causes a particular signal to perform its operation",
            "c) It causes a particular signal to end",
            "d) It increments the step counter by one"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The signal is generated using the logic of the formula above."
    },
    {
        "id": 454,
        "Question": "The benefit of using this approach is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is cost effective",
            "b) It is highly efficient",
            "c) It is very reliable",
            "d) It increases the speed of operation"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The RUN signal increments the step counter by one for each clock cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 455,
        "Question": "The disadvantage/s of the hardwired approach is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It is less flexible",
            "b) It cannot be used for complex instructions",
            "c) It is costly",
            "d) less flexible & cannot be used for complex instructions"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In other words hardwired is another name for Hardware Control signal generator."
    },
    {
        "id": 456,
        "Question": "In micro-programmed approach, the signals are generated by ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Machine instructions",
            "b) System programs",
            "c) Utility tools",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The machine instructions generate the signals."
    },
    {
        "id": 457,
        "Question": "A word whose individual bits represent a control signal is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Command word",
            "b) Control word",
            "c) Co-ordination word",
            "d) Generation word"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The control word is used to get the different types of control signals required."
    },
    {
        "id": 458,
        "Question": "A sequence of control words corresponding to a control sequence is called _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro routine",
            "b) Micro function",
            "c) Micro procedure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The micro routines are used to perform a particular task."
    },
    {
        "id": 459,
        "Question": "Individual control words of the micro routine are called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Micro task",
            "b) Micro operation",
            "c) Micro instruction",
            "d) Micro command"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The each instruction which put together performs the task."
    },
    {
        "id": 460,
        "Question": "The special memory used to store the micro routines of a computer is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control table",
            "b) Control store",
            "c) Control mart",
            "d) Control shop"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The control store is used as a reference to get the required control routine."
    },
    {
        "id": 461,
        "Question": "To read the control words sequentially _________ is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) PC",
            "b) IR",
            "c) UPC",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The UPC stands for Micro program counter."
    },
    {
        "id": 462,
        "Question": "Every time a new instruction is loaded into IR the output of ________ is loaded into UPC.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Starting address generator",
            "b) Loader",
            "c) Linker",
            "d) Clock"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The starting address generator is used to load the address of the next micro instruction."
    },
    {
        "id": 463,
        "Question": "The case/s where micro-programmed can perform well _______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) When it requires to check the condition codes",
            "b) When it has to choose between the two alternatives",
            "c) When it is triggered by an interrupt",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 464,
        "Question": "Highly encoded schemes that use compact codes to specify a small number of functions in each micro instruction is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Horizontal organisation",
            "b) Vertical organisation",
            "c) Diagonal organisation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This is done to improve the efficiency of the controller."
    },
    {
        "id": 465,
        "Question": "The surroundings of the recently accessed block is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Neighborhood",
            "b) Neighbour",
            "c) Locality of reference",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The position of each block is pre-determined in the direct mapped cache, hence no need for replacement."
    },
    {
        "id": 466,
        "Question": "The algorithm which replaces the block which has not been referenced for a while is called _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) LRU",
            "b) ORF",
            "c) Direct",
            "d) Both LRU and ORF"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The locality of reference is a key factor in many of the replacement algorithms."
    },
    {
        "id": 467,
        "Question": "In associative mapping during LRU, the counter of the new block is set to ‘0’ and all the others are incremented by one when _____ occurs.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delay",
            "b) Miss",
            "c) Hit",
            "d) Delayed hit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The above two methods of mapping the decision of which block to be removed rests with the cache controller."
    },
    {
        "id": 468,
        "Question": "The LRU provides very bad performance when it comes to _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Blocks being accessed is sequential",
            "b) When the blocks are randomised",
            "c) When the consecutive blocks accessed are in the extremes",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: LRU stands for Least Recently Used first."
    },
    {
        "id": 469,
        "Question": "The algorithm which removes the recently used page first is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LRU",
            "b) MRU",
            "c) OFM",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Miss usually occurs when the memory block required is not present in the cache."
    },
    {
        "id": 470,
        "Question": "In LRU, the referenced blocks counter is set to’0′ and that of the previous blocks are incremented by one and others remain same, in the case of ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hit",
            "b) Miss",
            "c) Delay",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The LRU in case of the sequential blocks as to waste its one cycle just incrementing the counters."
    },
    {
        "id": 471,
        "Question": "The counter that keeps track of how many times a block is most likely used is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Count",
            "b) Reference counter",
            "c) Use counter",
            "d) Probable counter"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In MRU it is assumed that the page accessed now is less likely to be accessed again."
    },
    {
        "id": 472,
        "Question": "The key factor/s in commercial success of a computer is/are ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Performance",
            "b) Cost",
            "c) Speed",
            "d) Both Performance and Cost"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The performance and cost of the computer system is a key decider in the commercial success of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 473,
        "Question": "The main objective of the computer system is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To provide optimal power operation",
            "b) To provide the best performance at low cost",
            "c) To provide speedy operation at low power consumption",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: An optimal system provides the best performance at low costs."
    },
    {
        "id": 474,
        "Question": "A common measure of performance is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Price/performance ratio",
            "b) Performance/price ratio",
            "c) Operation/price ratio",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: If this measure is less than one then the system is optimal."
    },
    {
        "id": 475,
        "Question": "The performance depends on ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The speed of execution only",
            "b) The speed of fetch and execution",
            "c) The speed of fetch only",
            "d) The hardware of the system only"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The performance of a system is decided by how quick an instruction is brought into the system and executed."
    },
    {
        "id": 476,
        "Question": "The main purpose of having memory hierarchy is to ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduce access time",
            "b) Provide large capacity",
            "c) Reduce propagation time",
            "d) Reduce access time & Provide large capacity"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: By using the memory Hierarchy, we can increase the performance of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 477,
        "Question": "An effective to introduce parallelism in memory access is by _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory interleaving",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) Pages",
            "d) Frames"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 478,
        "Question": "Two processors A and B have clock frequencies of 700 Mhz and 900 Mhz respectively. Suppose A can execute an instruction with an average of 3 steps and B can execute with an average of 5 steps. For the execution of the same instruction which processor is faster.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A",
            "b) B",
            "c) Both take the same time",
            "d) Insufficient information"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: Interleaving divides the memory into modules."
    },
    {
        "id": 479,
        "Question": "If the instruction Add R1, R2, R3 is executed in a system which is pipelined, then the value of S is (Where S is a term of the Basic performance equation).",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) ~2",
            "c) ~1",
            "d) 6"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This is so because the L1 cache is onboard the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 480,
        "Question": "The program is divided into operable parts called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frames",
            "b) Segments",
            "c) Pages",
            "d) Sheets"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This is one of the main reasons for the usage of virtual memories."
    },
    {
        "id": 481,
        "Question": "The techniques which move the program blocks to or from the physical memory is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Paging",
            "b) Virtual memory organisation",
            "c) Overlays",
            "d) Framing"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The program is divided into parts called as segments for ease of execution."
    },
    {
        "id": 482,
        "Question": "The binary address issued to data or instructions are called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Physical address",
            "b) Location",
            "c) Relocatable address",
            "d) Logical address"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: By using this technique the program execution is accomplished with a usage of less space."
    },
    {
        "id": 483,
        "Question": "__________ is used to implement virtual memory organisation.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Page table",
            "b) Frame table",
            "c) MMU",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The logical address is the random address generated by the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 484,
        "Question": "______ translates the logical address into a physical address.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMU",
            "b) Translator",
            "c) Compiler",
            "d) Linker"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The MMU stands for Memory Management Unit."
    },
    {
        "id": 485,
        "Question": "The main aim of virtual memory organisation is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To provide effective memory access",
            "b) To provide better memory transfer",
            "c) To improve the execution of the program",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The MMU translates the logical address into a physical address by adding an offset."
    },
    {
        "id": 486,
        "Question": "The virtual memory basically stores the next segment of data to be executed on the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Secondary storage",
            "b) Disks",
            "c) RAM",
            "d) ROM"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 487,
        "Question": "The associatively mapped virtual memory makes use of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) TLB",
            "b) Page table",
            "c) Frame table",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The DMA stands for Direct Memory Access, in which a block of data gets directly transferred from the memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 488,
        "Question": "The main reason for the discontinuation of semi conductor based storage devices for providing large storage space is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Lack of sufficient resources",
            "b) High cost per bit value",
            "c) Lack of speed of operation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In the case of semi conductor based memory technology, we get speed but the increase in the integration of various devices the cost is high."
    },
    {
        "id": 489,
        "Question": "The digital information is stored on the hard disk by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Applying a suitable electric pulse",
            "b) Applying a suitable magnetic field",
            "c) Applying a suitable nuclear field",
            "d) By using optic waves"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The digital data is sorted on the magnetized discs by magnetizing the areas."
    },
    {
        "id": 490,
        "Question": "For the synchronization of the read head, we make use of a _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Framing bit",
            "b) Synchronization bit",
            "c) Clock",
            "d) Dirty bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The clock makes it easy to distinguish between different values red by a head."
    },
    {
        "id": 491,
        "Question": "One of the most widely used schemes of encoding used is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) NRZ-polar",
            "b) RZ-polar",
            "c) Manchester",
            "d) Block encoding"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The Manchester encoding used is also called as phase encoding and it is used to encode both clock and data."
    },
    {
        "id": 492,
        "Question": "The drawback of Manchester encoding is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The cost of the encoding scheme",
            "b) The speed of encoding the data",
            "c) The Latency offered",
            "d) The low bit storage density provided"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The space required to represent each bit must be large enough to accommodate two changes in magnetization."
    },
    {
        "id": 493,
        "Question": "_____ pushes the heads away from the surface as they rotate at their standard rates.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Magnetic tension",
            "b) Electric force",
            "c) Air pressure",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: By maintaining the heads near to the surface greater bit densities can be achieved."
    },
    {
        "id": 494,
        "Question": "The air pressure can be countered by putting ______ in the head-disc surface arrangement.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Air filter",
            "b) Spring mechanism",
            "c) coolant",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: Due to the speed of rotation of the discs air pressure develops in the hard disk."
    },
    {
        "id": 495,
        "Question": "The method of placing the heads and the discs in an air tight environment is also called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAID Arrays",
            "b) ATP tech",
            "c) Winchester technology",
            "d) Fleming reduction"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The spring mechanism pushes the head along the surface to reduce the air pressure effect."
    },
    {
        "id": 496,
        "Question": "A hard disk with 20 surfaces will have _____ heads.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10",
            "b) 5",
            "c) 1",
            "d) 20"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The Disks and the heads operate faster due to the absence of the dust particles."
    },
    {
        "id": 497,
        "Question": "The set of corresponding tracks on all surfaces of a stack of disks form a ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cluster",
            "b) Cylinder",
            "c) Group",
            "d) Set"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 498,
        "Question": "The data can be accessed from the disk using _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Surface number",
            "b) Sector number",
            "c) Track number",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The data is stored in these sections called as cylinders."
    },
    {
        "id": 499,
        "Question": "The read and write operations usually start at ______ of the sector.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Center",
            "b) Middle",
            "c) From the last used point",
            "d) Boundaries"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 500,
        "Question": "To distinguish between two sectors we make use of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Inter sector gap",
            "b) Splitting bit",
            "c) Numbering bit",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The heads read and write data from the ends to the center."
    },
    {
        "id": 501,
        "Question": "The _____ process divides the disk into sectors and tracks.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Creation",
            "b) Initiation",
            "c) Formatting",
            "d) Modification"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This means that we leave a little gap between each sector to differentiate between them."
    },
    {
        "id": 502,
        "Question": "The access time is composed of __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seek time",
            "b) Rotational delay",
            "c) Latency",
            "d) Both Seek time and Rotational delay"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The formatting process deletes the data present and does the creation of sectors and tracks."
    },
    {
        "id": 503,
        "Question": "The disk drive is connected to the system by using the _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) PCI bus",
            "b) SCSI bus",
            "c) HDMI",
            "d) ISA"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The seek time refers to the time required to move the head to the required disk."
    },
    {
        "id": 504,
        "Question": "_______ is used to deal with the difference in the transfer rates between the drive and the bus.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data repeaters",
            "b) Enhancers",
            "c) Data buffers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 505,
        "Question": "_______ is used to detect and correct the errors that may occur during data transfers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ECC",
            "b) CRC",
            "c) Checksum",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The buffers are added to store the data from the fast device and to send it to the slower device at its rate."
    },
    {
        "id": 506,
        "Question": "The logic operations are implemented using _______ circuits.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Bridge",
            "b) Logical",
            "c) Combinatorial",
            "d) Gate"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The logic operation includes AND, OR, XOR etc."
    },
    {
        "id": 507,
        "Question": "The carry generation function: ci + 1 = yici + xici + xiyi, is implemented in ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Half adders",
            "b) Full adders",
            "c) Ripple adders",
            "d) Fast adders"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The combinatorial circuits means, using the basic universal gates."
    },
    {
        "id": 508,
        "Question": "Which option is true regarding the carry in the ripple adders?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Are generated at the beginning only",
            "b) Must travel through the configuration",
            "c) Is generated at the end of each operation",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In this the carry for the next step is generated in the previous steps operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 509,
        "Question": "In full adders the sum circuit is implemented using ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) And & or gates",
            "b) NAND gate",
            "c) XOR",
            "d) XNOR"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The carry must pass through the configuration of the circuit till it reaches the particular step."
    },
    {
        "id": 510,
        "Question": "The usual implementation of the carry circuit involves _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) And & or gates",
            "b) XOR",
            "c) NAND",
            "d) XNOR"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: sum = a ^ b ^ c (‘^’ indicates XOR operation)."
    },
    {
        "id": 511,
        "Question": "A _______ gate is used to detect the occurrence of an overflow.",
        "Options": [
            "a) NAND",
            "b) XOR",
            "c) XNOR",
            "d) AND"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In case of full and half adders this method is used."
    },
    {
        "id": 512,
        "Question": "In a normal adder circuit, the delay obtained in a generation of the output is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2n + 2",
            "b) 2n",
            "c) n + 2",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The overflow is detected by cn^cn-1 (‘^’ indicates XOR operation)."
    },
    {
        "id": 513,
        "Question": "The final addition sum of the numbers, 0110 & 0110 is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1101",
            "b) 1111",
            "c) 1001",
            "d) 1010"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The 2n delay cause of the carry generation and the 2 delay cause of the XOR operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 514,
        "Question": "The delay reduced to in the carry look ahead adder is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 5",
            "b) 8",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 2n"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 515,
        "Question": "The product of 1101 & 1011 is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 10001111",
            "b) 10101010",
            "c) 11110000",
            "d) 11001100"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The above operation is performed using binary multiplication."
    },
    {
        "id": 516,
        "Question": "We make use of ______ circuits to implement multiplication.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Flip flops",
            "b) Combinatorial",
            "c) Fast adders",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The fast adders are used to add the multiplied numbers."
    },
    {
        "id": 517,
        "Question": "The multiplier is stored in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) PC Register",
            "b) Shift register",
            "c) Cache",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The value is stored in a shift register so that each bit can be accessed separately."
    },
    {
        "id": 518,
        "Question": "The ______ is used to coordinate the operation of the multiplier.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Controller",
            "b) Coordinator",
            "c) Control sequencer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This performs the required sequencing of the various parts of the circuit."
    },
    {
        "id": 519,
        "Question": "The multiplicand and the control signals are passed through to the n-bit adder via _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) MUX",
            "b) DEMUX",
            "c) Encoder",
            "d) Decoder"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 520,
        "Question": "The product of -13 & 11 is ______________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1100110011",
            "b) 1101110001",
            "c) 1010101010",
            "d) 1111111000"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 521,
        "Question": "The method used to reduce the maximum number of summands by half is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Fast multiplication",
            "b) Bit-pair recording",
            "c) Quick multiplication",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer:  b\nExplanation: It reduces the number of summands by concatenating them."
    },
    {
        "id": 522,
        "Question": "The bits 1 & 1 are recorded as _______ in bit-pair recording.",
        "Options": [
            "a) -1",
            "b) 0",
            "c) +1",
            "d) both -1 and 0"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: Its ‘-1’  when the previous bit is 0 and ‘0’ when the previous bit is 1."
    },
    {
        "id": 523,
        "Question": "The multiplier -6(11010) is recorded as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0-1-2",
            "b) 0-1+1-10",
            "c) -2-10",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 524,
        "Question": "CSA stands for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Computer Speed Addition",
            "b) Carry Save Addition",
            "c) Computer Service Architecture",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The CSA is used to speed up the addition of multiplicands."
    },
    {
        "id": 525,
        "Question": "The numbers written to the power of 10 in the representation of decimal numbers are called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Height factors",
            "b) Size factors",
            "c) Scale factors",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: By doing this the computer is capable of accommodating the large float numbers also."
    },
    {
        "id": 526,
        "Question": "If the decimal point is placed to the right of the first significant digit, then the number is called ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Orthogonal",
            "b) Normalized",
            "c) Determinate",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: These are called as scale factors cause they’re responsible in determining the degree of specification of a number."
    },
    {
        "id": 527,
        "Question": "________ constitute the representation of the floating number.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Sign",
            "b) Significant digits",
            "c) Scale factor",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 528,
        "Question": "The sign followed by the string of digits is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Significant",
            "b) Determinant",
            "c) Mantissa",
            "d) Exponent"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The following factors are responsible for the representation of the number."
    },
    {
        "id": 529,
        "Question": "In IEEE 32-bit representations, the mantissa of the fraction is said to occupy ______ bits.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24",
            "b) 23",
            "c) 20",
            "d) 16"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The mantissa also consists of the decimal point."
    },
    {
        "id": 530,
        "Question": "The normalized representation of 0.0010110 * 2  9 is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 0 10001000 0010110",
            "b) 0 10000101 0110",
            "c) 0 10101010 1110",
            "d) 0 11110100 11100"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The mantissa is made to occupy 23 bits, with 8 bit exponent."
    },
    {
        "id": 531,
        "Question": "The 32 bit representation of the decimal number is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Double-precision",
            "b) Single-precision",
            "c) Extended format",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Normalized representation is done by shifting the decimal point."
    },
    {
        "id": 532,
        "Question": "In 32 bit representation the scale factor as a range of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) -128 to 127",
            "b) -256 to 255",
            "c) 0 to 255",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 533,
        "Question": "In double precision format, the size of the mantissa is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32 bit",
            "b) 52 bit",
            "c) 64 bit",
            "d) 72 bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: Since the exponent field has only 8 bits to store the value."
    },
    {
        "id": 534,
        "Question": "______  have been developed specifically for pipelined systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Utility software",
            "b) Speed up utilities",
            "c) Optimizing compilers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The compilers which are designed to remove redundant parts of the code are called as optimizing compilers."
    },
    {
        "id": 535,
        "Question": "The pipelining process is also called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Superscalar operation",
            "b) Assembly line operation",
            "c) Von Neumann cycle",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: It is called so because it performs its operation at the assembly level."
    },
    {
        "id": 536,
        "Question": "The fetch and execution cycles are interleaved with the help of ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Modification in processor architecture",
            "b) Clock",
            "c) Special unit",
            "d) Control unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The time cycle of the clock is adjusted to perform the interleaving."
    },
    {
        "id": 537,
        "Question": "Each stage in pipelining should be completed within ___________ cycle.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 1",
            "b) 2",
            "c) 3",
            "d) 4"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The stages in the pipelining should get completed within one cycle to increase the speed of performance."
    },
    {
        "id": 538,
        "Question": "If a unit completes its task before the allotted time period, then _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) It’ll perform some other task in the remaining time",
            "b) Its time gets reallocated to a different task",
            "c) It’ll remain idle for the remaining time",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This is done to avoid starvation of the longer task."
    },
    {
        "id": 539,
        "Question": "To increase the speed of memory access in pipelining, we make use of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Special memory locations",
            "b) Special purpose registers",
            "c) Cache",
            "d) Buffers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 540,
        "Question": "The periods of time when the unit is idle is called as _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stalls",
            "b) Bubbles",
            "c) Hazards",
            "d) Both Stalls and Bubbles"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: By using the cache we can reduce the speed of memory access by a factor of 10."
    },
    {
        "id": 541,
        "Question": "The contention for the usage of a hardware device is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural hazard",
            "b) Stalk",
            "c) Deadlock",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The stalls are a type of hazards that affect a pipelined system."
    },
    {
        "id": 542,
        "Question": "The situation wherein the data of operands are not available is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data hazard",
            "b) Stock",
            "c) Deadlock",
            "d) Structural hazard"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 543,
        "Question": "The throughput of a super scalar processor is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) less than 1",
            "b) 1",
            "c) More than 1",
            "d) Not Known"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The throughput of a processor is measured by using the number of instructions executed per second."
    },
    {
        "id": 544,
        "Question": "When the processor executes multiple instructions at a time it is said to use _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) single issue",
            "b) Multiplicity",
            "c) Visualization",
            "d) Multiple issues"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 545,
        "Question": "The ______ plays a very vital role in case of super scalar processors.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Compilers",
            "b) Motherboard",
            "c) Memory",
            "d) Peripherals"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The compilers are programmed to arrange the instructions to get more throughput."
    },
    {
        "id": 546,
        "Question": "If an exception is raised and the succeeding instructions are executed completely, then the processor is said to have ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Exception handling",
            "b) Imprecise exceptions",
            "c) Error correction",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The processor since as executed the following instructions even though an exception was raised, hence the exception is treated as imprecise."
    },
    {
        "id": 547,
        "Question": "In super-scalar processors, ________ mode of execution is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) In-order",
            "b) Post order",
            "c) Out of order",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The instructions are grouped meaning that the instructions fetch and decode and other cycles are overlapped."
    },
    {
        "id": 548,
        "Question": "Since it uses the out of order mode of execution, the results are stored in ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Buffers",
            "b) Special memory locations",
            "c) Temporary registers",
            "d) TLB"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: It follows out of order execution to speed up the execution of instructions."
    },
    {
        "id": 549,
        "Question": "The step where in the results stored in the temporary register is transferred into the permanent register is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Final step",
            "b) Commitment step",
            "c) Last step",
            "d) Inception step"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The results are stored in temporary locations and are arranged afterward."
    },
    {
        "id": 550,
        "Question": "A special unit used to govern the out of order execution of the instructions is called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Commitment unit",
            "b) Temporal unit",
            "c) Monitor",
            "d) Supervisory unit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 551,
        "Question": "The commitment unit uses a queue called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Record buffer",
            "b) Commitment buffer",
            "c) Storage buffer",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This unit monitors the execution of the instructions and makes sure that the final result is in order."
    },
    {
        "id": 552,
        "Question": "The CISC stands for ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Computer Instruction Set Compliment",
            "b) Complete Instruction Set Compliment",
            "c) Computer Indexed Set Components",
            "d) Complex Instruction set computer"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: CISC is a computer architecture where in the processor performs more complex operations in one step."
    },
    {
        "id": 553,
        "Question": "The computer architecture aimed at reducing the time of execution of instructions is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) CISC",
            "b) RISC",
            "c) ISA",
            "d) ANNA"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The RISC stands for Reduced Instruction Set Computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 554,
        "Question": "The Sun micro systems processors usually follow _____ architecture.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CISC",
            "b) ISA",
            "c) ULTRA SPARC",
            "d) RISC"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The Risc machine aims at reducing the instruction set of the computer."
    },
    {
        "id": 555,
        "Question": "The iconic feature of the RISC machine among the following is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Reduced number of addressing modes",
            "b) Increased memory size",
            "c) Having a branch delay slot",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The RISC processor design is more simpler than CISC and it consists of fewer transistors."
    },
    {
        "id": 556,
        "Question": "Both the CISC and RISC architectures have been developed to reduce the ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost",
            "b) Time delay",
            "c) Semantic gap",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: A branch delay slot is an instruction space immediately following a jump or branch."
    },
    {
        "id": 557,
        "Question": "Out of the following which is not a CISC machine.",
        "Options": [
            "a) IBM 370/168",
            "b) VAX 11/780",
            "c) Intel 80486",
            "d) Motorola A567"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The semantic gap is the gap between the high level language and the low level language."
    },
    {
        "id": 558,
        "Question": "Pipe-lining is a unique feature of _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) RISC",
            "b) CISC",
            "c) ISA",
            "d) IANA"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 559,
        "Question": "In CISC architecture most of the complex instructions are stored in _____",
        "Options": [
            "a) Register",
            "b) Diodes",
            "c) CMOS",
            "d) Transistors"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The RISC machine architecture was the first to implement pipe-lining."
    },
    {
        "id": 560,
        "Question": "Which of the architecture is power efficient?",
        "Options": [
            "a) CISC",
            "b) RISC",
            "c) ISA",
            "d) IANA"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: In CISC architecture more emphasis is given on the instruction set and the instructions take over a cycle to complete."
    },
    {
        "id": 561,
        "Question": "Any condition that causes a processor to stall is called as _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Hazard",
            "b) Page fault",
            "c) System error",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: An hazard causes a delay in the execution process of the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 562,
        "Question": "The periods of time when the unit is idle is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stalls",
            "b) Bubbles",
            "c) Hazards",
            "d) Both Stalls and Bubbles"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The stalls are a type of hazards that affect a pipe-lined system."
    },
    {
        "id": 563,
        "Question": "The contention for the usage of a hardware device is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Structural hazard",
            "b) Stalk",
            "c) Deadlock",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The processor contends for the usage of the hardware and might enter into a deadlock state."
    },
    {
        "id": 564,
        "Question": "The situation wherein the data of operands are not available is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Data hazard",
            "b) Stock",
            "c) Deadlock",
            "d) Structural hazard"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: Data hazards are generally caused when the data is not ready on the destination side."
    },
    {
        "id": 565,
        "Question": "The stalling of the processor due to the unavailability of the instructions is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control hazard",
            "b) structural hazard",
            "c) Input hazard",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The control hazard also called as instruction hazard is usually caused by a cache miss."
    },
    {
        "id": 566,
        "Question": "The time lost due to the branch instruction is often referred to as ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Latency",
            "b) Delay",
            "c) Branch penalty",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This time also retards the performance speed of the processor."
    },
    {
        "id": 567,
        "Question": "____________ method is used in centralized systems to perform out of order execution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Scorecard",
            "b) Score boarding",
            "c) Optimizing",
            "d) Redundancy"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The periods of time when the unit is idle is called a Bubble."
    },
    {
        "id": 568,
        "Question": "The algorithm followed in most of the systems to perform out of order execution is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Tomasulo algorithm",
            "b) Score carding",
            "c) Reader-writer algorithm",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: In a scoreboard, the data dependencies of every instruction are logged. Instructions are released only when the scoreboard determines that there are no conflicts with previously issued and incomplete instructions."
    },
    {
        "id": 569,
        "Question": "The problem where process concurrency becomes an issue is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Philosophers problem",
            "b) Bakery problem",
            "c) Bankers problem",
            "d) Reader-writer problem"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The Tomasulo algorithm is a hardware algorithm developed in 1967 by Robert Tomasulo from IBM. It allows sequential instructions that would normally be stalled due to certain dependencies to execute non-sequentially (out-of-order execution)."
    },
    {
        "id": 570,
        "Question": "The set of loosely connected computers are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LAN",
            "b) WAN",
            "c) Workstation",
            "d) Cluster"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: In a computer cluster all the participating computers work together on a particular task."
    },
    {
        "id": 571,
        "Question": "Each computer in a cluster is connected using __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UTP",
            "b) Rj-45",
            "c) STP",
            "d) Coaxial cable"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The computers are connected to each other using a LAN connector cable."
    },
    {
        "id": 572,
        "Question": "The computer cluster architecture emerged as a result of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) ISA",
            "b) Workstation",
            "c) Super computers",
            "d) Distributed systems"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: A distributed system is a computer system spread out over a geographic area."
    },
    {
        "id": 573,
        "Question": "The software which governs the group of computers is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Driver Rd45",
            "b) Interface UI",
            "c) Clustering middleware",
            "d) Distributor"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The software helps to project a single system image to the user."
    },
    {
        "id": 574,
        "Question": "The simplest form of a cluster is __________ approach.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Beowolf",
            "b) Sequoia",
            "c) Stone",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 575,
        "Question": "The cluster formation in which the work is divided equally among the systems is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Load-configuration",
            "b) Load-Division",
            "c) Light head",
            "d) Both Load-configuration and Load-Division"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This approach the work gets divided among the systems equally."
    },
    {
        "id": 576,
        "Question": "In the client server model of the cluster _________ approach is used.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Load configuration",
            "b) FIFO",
            "c) Bankers algorithm",
            "d) Round robin"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: By using this approach the performance of the cluster can be enhanced."
    },
    {
        "id": 577,
        "Question": "The beowolf structure follows the __________ approach of a relationship between the systems.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Master-slave",
            "b) Asynchronous",
            "c) Synchronous",
            "d) Isochronous"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 578,
        "Question": "The most common modes of communication in clusters are ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Message queues",
            "b) Message passing interface",
            "c) PVm",
            "d) Both Message passing interface and PVm"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 579,
        "Question": "The method followed in case of node failure, wherein the node gets disabled is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) STONITH",
            "b) Fibre channel",
            "c) Fencing",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 580,
        "Question": "VLIW stands for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Very Long Instruction Word",
            "b) Very Long Instruction Width",
            "c) Very Large Instruction Word",
            "d) Very Long Instruction Width"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: It is the architecture designed to perform multiple operations in parallel."
    },
    {
        "id": 581,
        "Question": "The important feature of the VLIW is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) ILP",
            "b) Cost effectiveness",
            "c) Performance",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: ILP stands for Instruction Level Parallelism."
    },
    {
        "id": 582,
        "Question": "The main difference between the VLIW and the other approaches to improve performance is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Cost effectiveness",
            "b) Increase in performance",
            "c) Lack of complex hardware design",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The Pipe-lining and super-scalar architectures involved the usage of complex hardware circuits for the implementation."
    },
    {
        "id": 583,
        "Question": "The parallel execution of operations in VLIW is done according to the schedule determined by __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Task scheduler",
            "b) Interpreter",
            "c) Compiler",
            "d) Encoder"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In other words, the order of execution of instructions has nothing to do with the physical hardware implementation of the system."
    },
    {
        "id": 584,
        "Question": "The VLIW processors are much simpler as they do not require of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Computational register",
            "b) Complex logic circuits",
            "c) SSD slots",
            "d) Scheduling hardware"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The compiler first checks the code for interdependencies and then determines the schedule for its execution."
    },
    {
        "id": 585,
        "Question": "The VLIW architecture follows _____ approach to achieve parallelism.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MISD",
            "b) SISD",
            "c) SIMD",
            "d) MIMD"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: As the compiler only decides the schedule of execution the schedule is not required here."
    },
    {
        "id": 586,
        "Question": "To compute the direction of the branch the VLIW uses _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Seekers",
            "b) Heuristics",
            "c) Direction counter",
            "d) Compass"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The MIMD stands for Multiple Instructions Multiple Data."
    },
    {
        "id": 587,
        "Question": "EPIC stands for?",
        "Options": [
            "a) Explicitly Parallel Instruction Computing",
            "b) External Peripheral Integrating Component",
            "c) External Parallel Instruction Computing",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The above mentioned instruction is a complex 48 bit instruction used to perform operations on floating numbers."
    },
    {
        "id": 588,
        "Question": "For converting a virtual address into the physical address, the programs are divided into __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pages",
            "b) Frames",
            "c) Segments",
            "d) Blocks"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: On the physical memory side the memory is divided into pages."
    },
    {
        "id": 589,
        "Question": "The pages size shouldn’t be too small, as this would lead to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfer errors",
            "b) Increase in operation time",
            "c) Increase in access time",
            "d) Decrease in performance"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: Each page might be allocated memory deferentially but the memory for one page will be continuous."
    },
    {
        "id": 590,
        "Question": "The cache bridges the speed gap between ______ and __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAM and ROM",
            "b) RAM and Secondary memory",
            "c) Processor and RAM",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The access time of the magnetic disk is much longer than the access time of the memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 591,
        "Question": "The virtual memory bridges the size and speed gap between __________ and __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) RAM and ROM",
            "b) RAM and Secondary memory",
            "c) Processor and RAM",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The Cache is a hardware implementation to reduce the access time for processor operations."
    },
    {
        "id": 592,
        "Question": "The higher order bits of the virtual address generated by the processor forms the _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Table number",
            "b) Frame number",
            "c) List number",
            "d) Page number"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The virtual memory basically works as an extension of the RAM."
    },
    {
        "id": 593,
        "Question": "The page length shouldn’t be too long because ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It reduces the program efficiency",
            "b) It increases the access time",
            "c) It leads to wastage of memory",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The higher order bits indicate the page number which points to one particular entry in the page table."
    },
    {
        "id": 594,
        "Question": "The lower order bits of the virtual address forms the __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Page number",
            "b) Frame number",
            "c) Block number",
            "d) Offset"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: If the size is more than the required size then the extra space gets wasted."
    },
    {
        "id": 595,
        "Question": "The area in the main memory that can hold one page is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Page entry",
            "b) Page frame",
            "c) Frame",
            "d) Block"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: This gives the offset within the page table."
    },
    {
        "id": 596,
        "Question": "The starting address of the page table is stored in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) TLB",
            "b) R0",
            "c) Page table base register",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 597,
        "Question": "The bits used to indicate the status of the page in the memory is called ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Control bits",
            "b) Status bits",
            "c) Progress bit",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: These bits are used to store the status information of the program."
    },
    {
        "id": 598,
        "Question": "The _______ bit is used to indicate the validity of the page.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Valid bit",
            "b) Invalid bit",
            "c) Correct bit",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The os first validates the page and then only moves from the page table."
    },
    {
        "id": 599,
        "Question": "The bit used to store whether the page has been modified or not is called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Dirty bit",
            "b) Modify bit",
            "c) Relocation bit",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This bit is set after the page in the table gets modified."
    },
    {
        "id": 600,
        "Question": "The page table should be ideally situated within ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) MMU",
            "d) Cache"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The page table information is used for every read and access operation."
    },
    {
        "id": 601,
        "Question": "If the page table is large then it is stored in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor",
            "b) Main memory",
            "c) Disk",
            "d) Secondary storage"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: By storing the table on the RAM the required operation’s speed is increased."
    },
    {
        "id": 602,
        "Question": "When the page table is placed in the main memory, the ___________ is used to store the recently accessed pages.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MMU",
            "b) TLB",
            "c) R0",
            "d) Table"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The TLB is used to store the page numbers of the recently accessed pages."
    },
    {
        "id": 603,
        "Question": "The TLB is incorporated as part of the _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Processor",
            "b) MMU",
            "c) Disk",
            "d) RAM"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 604,
        "Question": "Whenever a request to the page that is not present in the main memory is accessed ______ is triggered.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Interrupt",
            "b) Request",
            "c) Page fault",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: When a page fault is triggered, the os brings the required page into memory."
    },
    {
        "id": 605,
        "Question": "The general purpose registers are combined into a block called as ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Register bank",
            "b) Register Case",
            "c) Register file",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: To make the access of the registers easier, we classify them into register files."
    },
    {
        "id": 606,
        "Question": "What does the RUN signal do?",
        "Options": [
            "a) It causes the termination of a signal",
            "b) It causes a particular signal to perform its operation",
            "c) It causes a particular signal to end",
            "d) It increments the step counter by one"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The RUN signal increments the step counter by one for each clock cycle."
    },
    {
        "id": 607,
        "Question": "_____ register is designated to point to the 68000 processor stack.",
        "Options": [
            "a) A7 register",
            "b) B2 register",
            "c) There is no such designation",
            "d) Any general purpose register is selected at random"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The processor stack is the place used to store the ongoing and upcoming process information "
    },
    {
        "id": 608,
        "Question": "The word length in the 68000 computer is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32 bit",
            "b) 64 bit",
            "c) 16 bit",
            "d) 8 bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The length of an instruction that can be read or accessed at a time is referred to as word length.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 609,
        "Question": "The register in 68000 can contain up to _____ bits.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24",
            "b) 32",
            "c) 16",
            "d) 64"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The ability of a system to access the entire data of a process by reading consecutive bytes is called as Byte addressability "
    },
    {
        "id": 610,
        "Question": "The 68000 has a max of how many data registers?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16",
            "b) 20",
            "c) 10",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 611,
        "Question": "When an operand is stored in a register it is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Stored in the lower order bits of the register",
            "b) Stored in the higher order bits of the register",
            "c) Stored in any of the bits at random",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The data registers are solely used for the purpose of storing data items of the process."
    },
    {
        "id": 612,
        "Question": "The status register of the 68000 has ____ condition codes.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 7",
            "b) 4",
            "c) 5",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The data always gets stored from the lower order to the higher order bits, except in the case of Little Endian architecture."
    },
    {
        "id": 613,
        "Question": "The 68000 uses _____ address assignment.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Big Endian",
            "b) Little Endian",
            "c) X-Little Endian",
            "d) X-Big Endian"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The register which is used to basically store the condition flags is called as a status register."
    },
    {
        "id": 614,
        "Question": "The addresses generated by the 68000 is _____ bit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 32",
            "b) 16",
            "c) 24",
            "d) 42"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The way the data gets stored in a memory is called an address assignment."
    },
    {
        "id": 615,
        "Question": "Instructions which can handle any type of addressing mode are said to be ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Omniscient",
            "b) Orthogonal",
            "c) Versatile",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The size of the address is directly related to the address space of the system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 616,
        "Question": "As the instructions can deal with variable size operands we use ____________ to resolve this.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Delimiter",
            "b) Size indicator mnemonic",
            "c) Special assemblers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The operands are of different sizes because of the difference in the values."
    },
    {
        "id": 617,
        "Question": "The starting address is denoted using _________ directive.",
        "Options": [
            "a) EQU",
            "b) ORIGIN",
            "c) ORG",
            "d) PLACE"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: To indicate the size of the operand we use a separate variable mnemonic to indicate it."
    },
    {
        "id": 618,
        "Question": "The constant can be declared using ___________ directive.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DATAWORD",
            "b) PLACE",
            "c) CONS",
            "d) DC"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The starting address is the location where the program is stored."
    },
    {
        "id": 619,
        "Question": "To allocate a block of memory we use ___________ directive.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RESERVE",
            "b) DS",
            "c) DATAWORD",
            "d) PLACE"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: To declare Global constants we use this directive."
    },
    {
        "id": 620,
        "Question": "The Branch instruction in 68000 provides how many types of offsets?",
        "Options": [
            "a) 3",
            "b) 1",
            "c) 0",
            "d) 2"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 621,
        "Question": "The purpose of using DBcc as a branch instruction is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) It provides two conditions to be satisfied for a branch to occur",
            "b) It provides a counter to check the number of times the branch as taken place",
            "c) It is used to check the condition along with the branch condition",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The Branch instruction basically just adds a constant value to the address present in the PC, to change the instruction to be executed."
    },
    {
        "id": 622,
        "Question": "The 68000 uses ____________ method to access I/O devices buffers.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Memory mapped",
            "b) I/O mapped",
            "c) Buffer mapped",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None."
    },
    {
        "id": 623,
        "Question": "____________ instruction is used to set up a frame pointer for the subroutines in 68000.",
        "Options": [
            "a) CREATE",
            "b) LINK",
            "c) UNLK",
            "d) FRAME"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: In this method, both the I/O device and the memory share a common address space."
    },
    {
        "id": 624,
        "Question": "The LINK instruction is always followed by ____________ instruction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) MOV",
            "b) UNLK",
            "c) ORG",
            "d) MOVEM"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This pointer is used to monitor the stack."
    },
    {
        "id": 625,
        "Question": "ARM stands for _____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Advanced Rate Machines",
            "b) Advanced RISC Machines",
            "c) Artificial Running Machines",
            "d) Aviary Running Machines"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: ARM is a type of system architecture.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 626,
        "Question": "The main importance of ARM micro-processors is providing operation with ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Low cost and low power consumption",
            "b) Higher degree of multi-tasking",
            "c) Lower error or glitches",
            "d) Efficient memory management"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The Stand alone feature of the ARM processors is that they’re economically viable. "
    },
    {
        "id": 627,
        "Question": "ARM processors where basically designed for _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Main frame systems",
            "b) Distributed systems",
            "c) Mobile systems",
            "d) Super computers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: These ARM processors are designed for handheld devices. "
    },
    {
        "id": 628,
        "Question": "The address space in ARM is ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 224",
            "b) 264",
            "c) 216",
            "d) 232"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The ability to store data in the form of consecutive bytes. "
    },
    {
        "id": 629,
        "Question": "The address system supported by ARM systems is/are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Little Endian",
            "b) Big Endian",
            "c) X-Little Endian",
            "d) Both Little & Big Endian"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 630,
        "Question": "RISC stands for _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Restricted Instruction Sequencing Computer",
            "b) Restricted Instruction Sequential Compiler",
            "c) Reduced Instruction Set Computer",
            "d) Reduced Induction Set Computer"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The way in which, the data gets stored in the system or the way of address allocation is called as address system.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 631,
        "Question": "In the ARM, PC is implemented using ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Caches",
            "b) Heaps",
            "c) General purpose register",
            "d) Stack"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 632,
        "Question": "The additional duplicate register used in ARM machines are called as _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Copied-registers",
            "b) Banked registers",
            "c) EXtra registers",
            "d) Extential registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This is a system architecture, in which the performance of the system is improved by reducing the size of the instruction set. "
    },
    {
        "id": 633,
        "Question": "The banked registers are used for ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Switching between supervisor and interrupt mode",
            "b) Extended storing",
            "c) Same as other general purpose registers",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: PC is the place where the next instruction about to be executed is stored. "
    },
    {
        "id": 634,
        "Question": "Each instruction in ARM machines is encoded into __________ Word.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 2 byte",
            "b) 3 byte",
            "c) 4 byte",
            "d) 8 byte"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The duplicate registers are used in situations of context switching.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 635,
        "Question": "The addressing mode where the EA of the operand is the contents of Rn is ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Pre-indexed mode",
            "b) Pre-indexed with write back mode",
            "c) Post-indexed mode",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: When switching from one mode to another, instead of storing the register contents somewhere else it’ll be kept in the duplicate registers and the new values are stored in the actual registers. "
    },
    {
        "id": 636,
        "Question": "The effective address of the instruction written in Post-indexed mode, MOVE[Rn]+Rm is _______",
        "Options": [
            "a) EA = [Rn] ",
            "b) EA = [Rn  + Rm] ",
            "c) EA = [Rn] + Rm",
            "d) EA = [Rm] + Rn"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The data is encrypted to make them secure. "
    },
    {
        "id": 637,
        "Question": "___________ symbol is used to signify write back mode.",
        "Options": [
            "a) #",
            "b) ^",
            "c) &",
            "d) !"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 638,
        "Question": "The instructions which are used to load or store multiple operands are called as __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Banked instructions",
            "b) Lump transfer instructions",
            "c) Block transfer instructions",
            "d) DMA instructions"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: These instructions are generally used to perform memory transfer operations. "
    },
    {
        "id": 639,
        "Question": "The Instruction, LDM R10!, {R0,R1,R6,R7}  ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) Loads the contents of R10 into R1, R0, R6 and R7",
            "b) Creates a copy of the contents of R10 in the other registers except for the above mentioned ones",
            "c) Loads the contents of the registers R1, R0, R6 and R7 to R10",
            "d) Writes the contents of R10 into the above mentioned registers and clears R10"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The LDM instruction is used to load data into multiple locations.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 640,
        "Question": "The instruction, MLA R0,R1,R2,R3  performs _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R0<-[R1]+[R2]+[R3] ",
            "b) R3<-[R0]+[R1]+[R2] ",
            "c) R0<-[R1]*[R2]+[R3] ",
            "d) R3<-[R0]*[R1]+[R2]"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The MLA instruction is used perform addition and multiplication together."
    },
    {
        "id": 641,
        "Question": "The ability to shift or rotate in the same instruction along with other operation is performed with the help of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Switching circuit",
            "b) Barrel switcher circuit",
            "c) Integrated Switching circuit",
            "d) Multiplexer circuit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: These switching circuits are used to basically switch fast and to perform better.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 642,
        "Question": "_________ instruction is used to get the 1’s complement of the operand.",
        "Options": [
            "a) COMP",
            "b) BIC",
            "c) ~CMP",
            "d) MVN"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The complement of all the bits of a data is its 1’s compliment. "
    },
    {
        "id": 643,
        "Question": "The offset used in the conditional branching is __________ bit.",
        "Options": [
            "a) 24",
            "b) 32",
            "c) 16",
            "d) 8"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The offset is used to get the new branching address of the process. "
    },
    {
        "id": 644,
        "Question": "The BEQ instructions is used ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To check the equality condition between the operands and then branch",
            "b) To check if the Operand is greater than the condition value and then branch",
            "c) To check if the flag Z is set to 1 and then causes branch",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This instruction is basically used to check the branch enable bit. "
    },
    {
        "id": 645,
        "Question": "The condition to check whether the branch should happen or not is given by ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The lower order 8 bits of the instruction",
            "b) The higher order 4 bits of the instruction",
            "c) The lower order 4 bits of the instruction",
            "d) The higher order 8 bits of the instruction"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 646,
        "Question": "__________ directive is used to indicate the beginning of the program instruction or data.",
        "Options": [
            "a) EQU",
            "b) START",
            "c) AREA",
            "d) SPACE"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This instruction sets the condition flag without considering whether a carry or overflow has happened or not.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 647,
        "Question": "___________ directive specifies the start of the execution.",
        "Options": [
            "a) START",
            "b) ENTRY",
            "c) MAIN",
            "d) ORIGIN"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 648,
        "Question": "___________ directives are used to initialize operands.",
        "Options": [
            "a) INT",
            "b) DATAWORD",
            "c) RESERVE",
            "d) DCD"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This directive indicates the beginning of the executable part of the program.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 649,
        "Question": "___________ directive is used to name the register used for execution of an instruction.",
        "Options": [
            "a) ASSIGN",
            "b) RN",
            "c) NAME",
            "d) DECLARE"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: These directives are used to initialize the operands to a user defined value or a default value."
    },
    {
        "id": 650,
        "Question": "The pseudo instruction used to load an address into the register is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) LOAD",
            "b) ADR",
            "c) ASSIGN",
            "d) PSLOAD"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This instruction is used to list the registers used for execution.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 651,
        "Question": "The address space of the IA-32 is __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 216",
            "b) 232",
            "c) 264",
            "d) 28"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The number of addressable locations in the memory is called as address space. "
    },
    {
        "id": 652,
        "Question": "The addressing method used in IA-32 is ____________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Little Endian",
            "b) Big Endian",
            "c) X-Little Endian",
            "d) Both Little and Big Endian"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: The method of addressing the data in the system. "
    },
    {
        "id": 653,
        "Question": "The Floating point registers of IA-32 can operate on operands up to ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 128 bit",
            "b) 256 bit",
            "c) 80 bit",
            "d) 64 bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The floating registers are not stored in general purpose registers as they have a real part and a decimal part. "
    },
    {
        "id": 654,
        "Question": "The size of the floating registers can be extended upto _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 128 bit",
            "b) 256 bit",
            "c) 80 bit",
            "d) 64 bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The size of the floating numbers that can be stored in the floating register. "
    },
    {
        "id": 655,
        "Question": "The IA-32 architecture associates different parts of memory called __________ with different usages.",
        "Options": [
            "a) Frames",
            "b) Pages",
            "c) Tables",
            "d) Segments"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 656,
        "Question": "IOPL stands for ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Input/Output Privilege level",
            "b) Input Output Process Link",
            "c) Internal Output Process Link",
            "d) Internal Offset Privilege Level"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The memory is divided into parts called as segments. "
    },
    {
        "id": 657,
        "Question": "In IA-32 architecture along with the general flags, the other conditional flags provided are ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) IOPL",
            "b) IF",
            "c) TF",
            "d) All of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: Registers are not used to incorporate PC as in other architectures, but a separate space is allocated to it.   "
    },
    {
        "id": 658,
        "Question": "The register used to serve as PC is called as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Indirection register",
            "b) Instruction pointer",
            "c) R-32",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This indicates the security between the transfers between the I/O devices and memory. "
    },
    {
        "id": 659,
        "Question": "The Bit extension of the register is denoted with the help of __________ symbol.",
        "Options": [
            "a) $",
            "b) `",
            "c) E",
            "d) ~"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: These flags are basically used to check the system for exceptions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 660,
        "Question": "The instruction, ADD R1, R2, R3 is decoded as ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) R1<-[R1]+[R2]+[R3] ",
            "b) R3<-[R1]+[R2] ",
            "c) R3<-[R1]+[R2]+[R3] ",
            "d) R1<-[R2]+[R3]"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: The PC is used to store the next instruction that is going to be executed. "
    },
    {
        "id": 661,
        "Question": "The instruction JG loop does ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) jumps to the memory location loop if the result of the most recent arithmetic op is even",
            "b) jumps to the memory location loop if the result of the most recent arithmetic op is greater than 0",
            "c) jumps to the memory location loop if the test condition is satisfied with the value of loop",
            "d) none of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This switching enables a wide range of operations to be performed.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 662,
        "Question": "The LEA mnemonic is used to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Load the effective address of an instruction",
            "b) Load the values of operands onto an accumulator",
            "c) Declare the values as global constants",
            "d) Store the outcome of the operation at a memory location"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This is used to extend the size of the register. "
    },
    {
        "id": 663,
        "Question": "The instructions of IA-32 machines are of length up to ______",
        "Options": [
            "a) 4 bytes",
            "b) 8 bytes",
            "c) 16 bytes",
            "d) 12 bytes"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: The size of instruction that can be executed at once. "
    },
    {
        "id": 664,
        "Question": "The bit present in the op code, indicating which of the operands is the source is called as ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) SRC bit",
            "b) Indirection bit",
            "c) Direction bit",
            "d) FRM bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 665,
        "Question": "The __________ directive is used to allocate 4 bytes of memory.",
        "Options": [
            "a) DD",
            "b) ALLOC",
            "c) RESERVE",
            "d) SPACE"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 666,
        "Question": ".data directive is used _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) To indicate the ending of the data section",
            "b) To indicate the beginning of the data section",
            "c) To declare all the source operands",
            "d) To Initialize the operands"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This is used to indicate the starting of the section of data. "
    },
    {
        "id": 667,
        "Question": "The instruction used to cause unconditional jump is ________",
        "Options": [
            "a) UJG",
            "b) JG",
            "c) JMP",
            "d) GOTO"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: This statement causes a jump from one instruction to another without the condition.  "
    },
    {
        "id": 668,
        "Question": "__________ instruction is used to check the bit of the condition flags.",
        "Options": [
            "a) TEST",
            "b) TB",
            "c) CHECK",
            "d) BT"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: This is used to check the condition flags for exceptions. "
    },
    {
        "id": 669,
        "Question": "REPINS instruction is used to __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Transfer a block of data serially from an Input device to the processor",
            "b) Transfer a block of data parallelly from Input device to the processor",
            "c) Transfer a block of data serially from an Input device to the output device",
            "d) Transfer a block of data parallelly from Input device to the output device"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 670,
        "Question": "The instruction used to multiply operands yielding a double integer outcome is _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) MUL",
            "b) IMUL",
            "c) DMUL",
            "d) EMUL"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: The stack is a data structure which is fixed at one end and grows at the other. "
    },
    {
        "id": 671,
        "Question": "SIMD stands for __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) Single Instruction Multiple Data",
            "b) Simple Instruction Multiple Decoding",
            "c) Sequential Instruction Multiple Decoding",
            "d) System Information Mutable Data"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This instruction is used to carry out multiplication on large integral values. "
    },
    {
        "id": 672,
        "Question": "The IA-32 system follows _________ design.",
        "Options": [
            "a) RISC",
            "b) CISC",
            "c) SIMD",
            "d) None of the mentioned"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: a\nExplanation: This is the instruction used to perform an operation on multiple types of data."
    },
    {
        "id": 673,
        "Question": "Which architecture is suitable for a wide range of data types?",
        "Options": [
            "a) ARM",
            "b) 68000",
            "c) IA-32",
            "d) ASUS firebird"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: b\nExplanation: This system architecture is used to reduce the steps involved in execution by performing complex operations in one step. "
    },
    {
        "id": 674,
        "Question": "In case of multimedia extension instructions, the pixels are encoded into a data item of _________",
        "Options": [
            "a) 16 bit",
            "b) 32 bit",
            "c) 24 bit",
            "d) 8 bit"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 675,
        "Question": "The MMX (Multimedia Extension) operands are stored in __________",
        "Options": [
            "a) General purpose registers",
            "b) Banked registers",
            "c) Float point registers",
            "d) Graphic registers"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: d\nExplanation: None. "
    },
    {
        "id": 676,
        "Question": "The division operation in IA-32 is a single operand instruction so it is assumed that ___________",
        "Options": [
            "a) The divisor is stored in the EAX register",
            "b) The dividend is stored in the EAC register",
            "c) The divisor is stored in the accumulator",
            "d) The dividend is stored in the accumulator"
        ],
        "Answer": "  Answer: c\nExplanation: These operands are used for graphic related operations. "
    }
]